<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Six sermons lately preached in the parish church of Gouahurst in Kent. And afterwards, most maliciously charged with the titles of odious, blasphemous, Popish, and superstitious, preaching. / Now published by the author, I. W.</title>
            <author>Wilcock, James, d. 1662.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 210 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96477</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2118</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E172_30</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16426</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860032</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860032</idno>
            <idno type="VID">112137</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96477)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 112137)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 30:E172[30])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Six sermons lately preached in the parish church of Gouahurst in Kent. And afterwards, most maliciously charged with the titles of odious, blasphemous, Popish, and superstitious, preaching. / Now published by the author, I. W.</title>
                  <author>Wilcock, James, d. 1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 76 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I. Raworth,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Dom. 1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "ilcoke" is inserted following 'I. W.' in title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:112137:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SIX SERMONS LATELY Preached in the Pariſh CHURCH of <hi>Gouahurſt</hi> in KENT.</p>
            <p>And afterwards, moſt maliciouſly charged with the Titles Of
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Odious,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Blaſphemous,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Popiſh,</hi> and</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Superſtitious,</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> Preaching.</p>
            <p>Now publiſhed by the Author, <hi>I. Wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>coks</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>TACIT.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Si accuſari fas eſt, nulli licebit eſſe innocenti.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>I. Raworth.</hi> Anno Dom. 1641.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:112137:2"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="2+ pages">
                  <desc>〈2… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>blaſphemy, falſe doctrine, and odious preaching, leading of ſouls to hell: I could have borne innumerable other outrages, and laſhes of their tongues; but God only knows how much my ſoul hath been over charged with theſe imputations. It is not my caſe alone, others of my brethren, infinitely deſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ving better; have been engaged as deeply:</hi> Our backes are daily plowed upon, they ſay unto our ſouls, ly down that we may go over. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>The Lord will ſurely awake out of ſleep; He ſeems to them,</hi> Non advertere quia non a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>imadvertere; <hi>and becauſe puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is not preſently executed, they ſwell in the proſperity of their proceedings: But he will ſhortly ſhew; that theſe things have been both</hi> viſa &amp; inviſa, <hi>he hath ſeen that their time is coming, and therefore lets them rige. I ſhall with patience poſſeſſe my ſoul; and commend my cauſe to God, and my juſt excuſe to thee, Chriſtian Reader, whoſe I am in Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:112137:2"/>
            <head>THE FIRST SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>JOHN 20. Verſe 19, 20.</bibl>
               <q>He ſayd unto them, Peace be unto you: and when be had ſayd, be ſhewed them his hands and his ſide.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He words are the ſalutation of an Apoſtle, of an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle to the Apoſtles; he which was the Apoſtle of the Fathers ſending verſ. 21. to them which were Apoſtles of his own; they are his own words a little after, <hi>as the father ſent me, ſo ſend I you:</hi> But the <hi>ſicut</hi> there, is not <hi>aequalitatis,</hi> but <hi>proportion is,</hi> ſaith <hi>Maldonate;</hi> in regard of the manner of his miſſion, and the matter of his commiſſion there was indeed a <hi>non ſicut;</hi> the work of mediation was only his, of miniſtration theirs; he was to purchaſe, they to publiſh; He was <hi>pax noſtra,</hi> ſo ſaith th' Apoſtle; they but <hi>praecones pacis,</hi> ſaith the Prophet, meſſengers of peace; yet in regard of the authority of the miſſion, and the efficacy of the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, there was a ſimilitude; their hard fortune in the world, their courſe entertainment amongſt Wolves, (I might inſtance in other matters, but that it is not proper to this Text) may very well be ſuffered to carry ſome proportion; Amongſt the reſt there was a <hi>ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cut</hi> in this, this ſalutation in the Text: when he ſent them the firſt word, he appointed them to ſay were, <hi>Peace he to this houſe, Luke</hi> 10. 5. And now he whom the Father had ſent comes un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o them with the ſame ſalutation, to ſhew that he and they were of the ſame miſſion, <hi>Peace he unto you; and when he had ſaid ſo, be ſhewed them his hands and his feet.</hi> I ſhall not need to tell you that theſe words were a uſuall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement amongſt the Jewes; they practiſe it within themſelves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o this preſent; <hi>Peace he unto you,</hi> is their ſalutation: even when war is in their heart, they would have peace in their mouthes, and make the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:112137:3"/> 
               <hi>ſymb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll</hi> of love and friendſhip, a mask of falſhood and treaſon: to that effect <hi>Joab</hi> greeted <hi>Amaſa</hi> in the 2 <hi>Sam. 20. 9. Art thou in health my brother?</hi> but he ſhewed him neither his hand nor his ſide; for there he covertly held his ſword, with which treacherouſly he ſlew him. Little better is much of the only complement of theſe times, whoſe words are ſmoother then butter, and yet are they very ſword<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. But there was no matter of any ſuch miſtruſt from theſe words of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, and to prevent all ſuſpition which poſſibly might ariſe, aſſoon as he had ſaid them, <hi>He ſhewed them his hands and his ſide.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Indeed the Diſciples were afraid, ſo Saint <hi>Luke</hi> ſaith, <hi>chap</hi> 24. 37. they had but lately beheld the ſad <hi>Tragedy</hi> of their Maſters ſufferings, and like a trembling Herd when their choiſeſt Hart was ſmitten down, fled amazedly diſtracted at the fall; they looked every hour when themſelves ſhould be marked out for the ſlaugh er by thoſe hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry woodmen. They were at this time <hi>aſſembled together for fear of the Jewes,</hi> (the words before my Text) <hi>and the doors were ſhut;</hi> and our Saviours ſudden and inviſible apparition had been enough to have frighted them being in that terrour, if he had not preſently ſayd unto them, <hi>Peace be unto you,</hi> and <hi>ſhewed them his hands and his ſide.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet whether they miſtruſted ſome poyſon might lie in that courtſhip, remembring what treaſon was of late interred in a kiſſe; or whether fear had ſo much eſtranged them, that they werenot come to themſelves when Chriſt ſpake, and ſo gave no attention to what was ſaid; he is fain to repeat the ſame over again; and that he might not loſe in their acceptance that which he thought they would ſo h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>hly prize, ſaith <hi>Maldonate,</hi> he ſaith unto them again, <hi>Peace be unto you,</hi> verſe 21. and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aint <hi>Luke</hi> ſaith, <hi>again he ſhewed them his hands and his feet.</hi> Chriſt had received this praiſe in the Goſpel, that he did both <hi>do, and teach, Acts</hi> 1. 1. and that he was <hi>mighty indeed, and in word, Luke</hi> 24. 19. He practiſed ever himſelf firſt, what he taught others, and though never man ſpake like him, yet his works made a far better report of him then his words, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5. 36. Indeed he was ſent to bring the bleſſing, and thoſe come to ſteal it rather which come with the voice of <hi>Jacob,</hi> but the hands of <hi>Eſau:</hi> Thoſe which will be right bringers of it, muſt when they come ſhew their hands and their feet; then will they ſay like thoſe in <hi>Eſay 52. 7. How beautifull are the feet of them, which declare and publiſh peace!</hi> Chriſt had purchaſed peace; the wounds in his hands, and ſide, and feet were <hi>the chaſtiſements of our peace,</hi> ſo the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> calls them, <hi>Eſay</hi> 53. 5. and now he
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:112137:3"/> comes to publiſh it to his Diſciples; and that his laſt act might be made up of a perfect harmony, he brings the Trophees of his victory, the wounds of his body, to ſhew them how and upon what termes he had purchaſed it for them: <hi>He ſaid unto them, Peace be unto you, and when he had ſo ſayd, he ſhewed them his hands and his ſide.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If we attend only the ſalutation of our Saviour, there were not much to be ſpoken, it was common to others as well; yet it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable in this, His Diſciples had all of them either cowardly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en, or ſhamefully denyed him, they abode not by him at the firſt skirmiſh, he was left alone unto the ſhock, and there was none elſe; now he was returned a victorious champion, having broken through the ſteely ribs and braz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n bars of death and the grave; and that he ſhould at the firſt word proclaim peace unto thoſe traytors, that not ſued, not ſought unto, he ſhould embrace thoſe fugitives, is contrary unto moſt of the practice of the world, ſuch a greeting doth ill agree with ſuch as they; Curſes upon ſuch occaſions are more in ure then bleſſings; the ſword one would have thought had been more due then peace; but it becomes not Chriſt to be the meſſenger of war; He brought wounds but in his own hands and ſide; he would not give any, though he was content to receive. Such is the mercy of our God ſtill unto us ſinners, he is not <hi>Aeſtimator meriti,</hi> but <hi>largitor ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niae,</hi> as our Church calls him in her Liturgie.</p>
            <p>But there is more in it then ſo, <hi>Aliter a Chriſto, quàm a mundo ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutamur,</hi> ſaith <hi>Maldonate:</hi> it is not for nothing, that contrary to the form of ſalutation, he doth preſently upon the matter repeat the ſame words, verſ. 21. he goeth over it, and over it again, to ſhew that he would not have it ſingly regarded; or as <hi>Pharaohs</hi> dreams were doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to confirm the viſion, ſo are his words to make good his ſaluta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; <hi>Pacem ſubinde dicit, ut p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hello ſolamen afferat,</hi> ſaith <hi>Chriſ ſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if we conſider the quality of the peace, we ſhall finde it to anſwer the greatneſſe of the war; before war <hi>Jehues</hi> reply to <hi>Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram</hi> ſorted well to every one of us, what had we to do with peace? after war, ſo chargeable a war as our Saviour had ſo lately underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, it is not likely an unworthy peace could be accepted; as is the man, ſuch is his m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſage, you ſhall hear more of the worth of both anon.</p>
            <p>I had ere now taken the Text aſunder, but that I thought I ought not raſhly to have entred it without ſome ſalutation: I muſt now a while diſturbe the peace of the Text, that I may the better diſcover
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:112137:4"/> unto you the Text of peace. The violation which ſhall be offered, will be redreſſed by the union: A diviſion which is but <hi>morall,</hi> not <hi>mortall,</hi> will be the better reliſhed in the cloſe: I ſhall at laſt with more eaſe leave it as I finde it, then finde how or where to leave it.</p>
            <p>Two words take up the whole Text.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 Peace, and</item>
               <item>2 The price of it.</item>
            </list>
            <p>1. The publiſhing of peace. 2. The purchaſing of it. In the firſt is <hi>verbum pacis.</hi> In the ſecond <hi>factum pacis:</hi> and when words and works concur, is like to be trueſt peace. Or elſe thus, There is firſt the bleſſing of peace, that is the matter of the Text. Secondly the author of peace, 1. <hi>Pax Dei. 2. Deus pacis.</hi> And he is</p>
            <p>Two wayes the author of peace. 1. By Miniſtration. 2. By medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation. 1. By publiſhing. 2. By purchaſing; the meſſenger, the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker is one, he which brought it in the firſt words of the Text, <hi>Peace be unto you,</hi> firſt bought it in the latter, and for that end <hi>he ſhewed them his hands and his ſide.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, the publiſhing of peace is two wayes. Firſt, <hi>optatively,</hi> by way of wiſhing. Secondly, <hi>imparatively,</hi> by way of commanding. In the firſt, <hi>Pax vohis,</hi> he wiſheth peace to us, he wiſheth us to it; and therefore ſome of the Fathers have called this more then a ſalutation, <hi>votum Chriſti;</hi> In the ſecond, <hi>Pax vohis,</hi> is as much as, <hi>pacem habete in vohis;</hi> and therefore more yet, than <hi>votum Chriſti,</hi> it is <hi>mandatum Chriſti.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here will come in at laſt to be conſidered, the perſons to whom it is proclaimed, for whom it was purchaſed, <hi>vohis, Peace be unto you: and when he had ſo ſayd, he ſhewed them his hands and his ſide.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We begin with the firſt, the bleſſing of peace, 1. <hi>Pax Dei.</hi> It will be too hard a task to make you underſtand that which the Scripture ſaith doth paſſe all underſtanding. The Kingdome of God ſaith the Apoſtle conſiſts in three things, (whereof peace bears the greateſt part) <hi>Righteouſneſſe, Peace,</hi> and <hi>Joy,</hi> Rom. 14. 17. <hi>Opus juſtitiae, Pax Letitia, offectum pacis:</hi> Joy could not have been at all without righteouſneſſe, righteouſneſſe alone could not have brought forth joy; upon thoſe termes we ſtood till Peace was brought into the world purchaſd and proclaimed: Thoſe two extreams, Gods ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and our joy had never come together, till Peace came in the midſt and concluded for us.</p>
            <p>Now peace, is that which all things wiſh, it is <hi>votum,</hi> and <hi>ſumma
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:112137:4"/> vo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orum: Aquinas</hi> calleth it, the <hi>ſummum bonum</hi> of all things. Reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Creatures the Angels in Heaven they deſire to bring the news of peace, <hi>Pax terris, Luke</hi> 2. The devils in hell would be glad of it to; The very enimy of peace to have peace himſelf, he would not be tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, nor troubled that troubles all things elſe, unreaſonable Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, fire and water, whiles they are together, nothing buſtles more, when aſunder nothing ioyes more in their ſeparation, they fight that they may be at peace all: even ſenceleſſe things are at an unreſt till in their place, to which naturally they tend in, which only they be at peace; even God himſelf wiſheth ſo well to peace, that as if he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred it before all his other Titles, he loves to be ſtiled <hi>Deus Pacis,</hi> the God of Peace.</p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> places it in order, and cals it <hi>tranquillitas ordinis:</hi> as the <hi>Symmetry</hi> among the members when none are out of place; the <hi>Harmony</hi> in muſick, when no one note is harſh, or out of tune, ſuch is peace and order among eſtates. <hi>Maximus</hi> cals it, <hi>ejus quod gratiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum eſt plena poſſeſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o,</hi> when the deſire hath its full complement of what moſt delights it: therefore happineſſe is by ſome ſaid to be <hi>Pax deſiderii,</hi> when our deſire hath what it would, then it will be at reſt, not before; then it will have peace; But that is not to be had here in this life, not that peace which may eſtate us in a full and quiet poſſeſſion of all things we could wiſh for; it is but <hi>deſiderium Pacis</hi> here; we muſt therefore make two ſorts of peace with the School. 1. <hi>Perfecta.</hi> 2. <hi>Imperfecta,</hi> The one is <hi>Patriae</hi> of the bleſſed Saints and Angels there; the other is <hi>Viae</hi> of the toſſed ſouls and Pilgrims here: that conſiſts in a Vnion to one eternall good, this chiefly in Communion.</p>
            <p>The firſt, <hi>Pax vohis,</hi> ſitting enough for Chriſt to wiſh, but not as yet for you to receive; you are yet but in the way to it; and yet that we may not altogether exclude from the Text. Chriſt purchaſed that for you, the peace of God, and therefore it belongs unto you. The glorified Saints in heaven enjoy it by right of redemption from him, by vertue of the price which he paid for it: you may joy in it here, but not enioy it; the remembrance of it will make you love peace the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter whiles you live, and teach you to keep peace here, which to the preſervers of it, is a <hi>Symboll</hi> and token of that bleſſed peace there.</p>
            <p>But the peace is to be ſtated according to this life, and that is but <hi>imperfect;</hi> at the beſt but imperfectly perfect: it is three-fold; and to note that <hi>Tribus vicibus pace<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> dicit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:112137:5"/>1. Peace in heaven with God above us, that is <hi>Pax aeterna,</hi> it is but begun here in this life, and they have it to whom Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Pax vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>his;</hi> there was a warre betwixt God and us; he was become our enemy, and in that great inundation had ſwept us all away for ever, but that Chriſt, like the Dove with the Olive Branch in his mouth, brought us peace, reconciled us to him; he is our peace which hath made of both one, ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1. 14. he which was <hi>factus u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us ex utra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que</hi> one Perſon of two natures, was <hi>faciens utram<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> unam,</hi> two na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures into one peace.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Peace within us with our own hearts, <hi>Pax interna:</hi> that <hi>Caro ſemper militat contra Spiritum,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Chryſost. Tom. 1. p</hi> 1. 41. It is not ſo much, that that war is to be ſtill continued, there can be no peace there, till a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l the luſts be ſubdued: God forbade <hi>Iſrael</hi> to make any peace with the <hi>Cinaanite,</hi> victory onely which will not be till death muſt put an end to the Battell. But beſides, there is a warre not onely againſt the ſoul, but in the ſoul, <hi>in ſinu,</hi> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſoul it ſelf is woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and caſt down, and overthrown; it lies upon a Bed of thornes, between hope and fear, between faith and fainting; ſome have been ſo deeply engaged in it, that they wou'd have rid themſelves of their ſouls to be rid of it, but now a peace here is concluded, a peace made with God above; and ſoon will there be peace in our hearts within: whiles the Lord of Hoſts was up in arms the very powers and forces of the ſoul muſtered themſelves againſt her ſelf, but now he is down, and is reconciled: <hi>Why art thou ſo vexed, O my ſoul? and why art thou ſo diſquieted within me?</hi> and why ſay you then you rebelling fears, unto my ſoul, that ſhe ſhould <hi>fly as a bird unto the hill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Peace with others without us, <hi>Pax externa:</hi> the Angels pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed this from heaven at the Birth of our Saviour, <hi>pax terris:</hi> and all the world was then at peace, in token whereof <hi>Janus</hi> was ſhut up. I ſhall not doubt to ſay that this peace (peace amongſt men) is part of our Saviours wiſh, and of his will too, and therefore when he ſent his diſciples, he bade them ever ſay firſt, <hi>pax buic Domui,</hi> and we know how much the Apoſtles preach it, as their Lord commanded them. Civill peace is after ſpirituall, the greateſt of Gods bleſſings, with it an <hi>band full of herbs</hi> how ſweet is it? without it an <hi>houſe full of Sacrifice,</hi> what good is it? Therefore the Primitive Church, ſaith <hi>Tertullian,</hi> ever uſed to pray for it, <hi>orbem pacatum;</hi> and the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> bids us re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member to do it, <hi>Oh pray for the peace of Jeruſalem, they ſhall proſper that love it,</hi> Pſal. 122. 6. <hi>They ſhall have joy that counſell it, Prov.</hi> 12. 20.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:112137:5"/> 
               <hi>They ſhall be bleſſed that make it,</hi> Matth. 5. 9. How great a reward ſhould he finde in heaven? how glorious a name ſhall he leave upon earth that could bring it to paſſe?</p>
            <p>I paſſe unto the next, the Author and Giver of Peace, the God of peace. Chriſt himſelf is the Author of it; <hi>omnis benedictio a majore,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, and no bleſſing greater than peace, none greater to give it than Chriſt; when he was born, it was <hi>Zenium Christi,</hi> ſo St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> calls it, <hi>Encaenium Chriſti,</hi> ſo <hi>Bonaventure.</hi> The chief part of the Angels ſong, <hi>Peace on earth;</hi> his firſt gift when he went away, it was <hi>Donativum Christi,</hi> my peace I give unto you, my peace I leave with you: his laſt Legacy; men uſe at the laſt, to give their beſt things unto their friends. and Chriſt had no better then peace to give; he gave it by way of Teſtament then, upon his Good-Friday farewell, by way of Teſtimony he renews it now as upon his Eaſter Salutation, that he might remember them afreſh now, of what ſo late he bequeathed them then, ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome.</hi> It was the laſt thing he thought on before his death, it is the firſt thing he thinks on now after his riſing, the firſt and the laſt with Chriſt, and yet for the moſt part the laſt and the leaſt with us Chriſtians; and to ſhew how much himſelf was the cauſe of peace, he is called <hi>Pax noſtra, Epheſ.</hi> 2. 14. And every where in the New Teſtament, <hi>Deus Pacis,</hi> and God as if he took better liking to that Title, then any of his other, is no where ſince ſtiled <hi>Deminus Sabaoth,</hi> but <hi>Sabbath,</hi> not of hoaſts, but of reſt, not of power but of peace.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Now he is the Author of peace; ſo the Church in one of her collects cals him two wayes. 1. By <hi>Miniſtration,</hi> he was not content the Angels only ſhould be Heralds of it, or that men alone ſhould be <hi>Evangelizantes pacem:</hi> himſelf came to Miniſter, to grace our Functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the better, and if of any thing, it is moſt fit that he ſhould be the Miniſter of the beſt things; It was neceſſary that peace ſhould be publiſhed, there will be no laying down of Armes till then: but why Chriſt himſelf ſhould be the Miniſter of it, was ſure to ſet the greater price on his peace, to ſhew its dignity, his dignation, he which bought it, alſo brought it, the Make<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of our peace would be the Meſſenger of it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. And now he brings it. 1. <hi>Optatively,</hi> by way of wiſhing, <hi>Peace be unto you.</hi> Thoſe ever ought to do that at leaſt which ſay it, there ought to be an intendment at leaſt of peace, if it cannot be had, yet it were to be wiſhed, to be ſincerely deſired; there ſhould be
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:112137:6"/> 
               <hi>votum pacis in corde,</hi> as well as <hi>vox pacis in ore:</hi> or elſe twere fairer dealing to march on furiouſly with <hi>Jehu,</hi> to ſay plainly, what haſt thou to do with peace? then falſely with <hi>Jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b</hi> and <hi>Judos</hi> to ſalute and kiſſe, and to betray and kill. It is pitty that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Language of Heaven ſhould ever uſher in any project of hell, that black purpoſes ſhould come cloathed with the whiteſt Ornaments, that dark fiends ſhould ſpeak like glorified Spirits, and under pretence of prayers devoure up houſes, under the colours of peace, contrive miſchief and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>But our Saviour intended it ſure, and therefore wiſheth it to them, and in it whatſoever elſe goods to be wiſhed for; Peace is the Breviary of all votes, <hi>Pacem te poſcimus omnes:</hi> The Apoſtle cals <hi>Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zantes pacem, Evangelizantes bona, Rom.</hi> 10. 15. As if all good things were in peace, that is the beſt comment upon this complement, they which wiſh us peace, wiſh us all good things: beſides, both <hi>Bonum jucundum &amp; foecundum,</hi> they are the chief goods; we look after plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant and profitable goods. Peace is both th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſaith, <hi>Pſal. 133. Behold how good and pleaſant a thing it is, like A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rons oyntment,</hi> it is <hi>bonum amabile,</hi> and like <hi>the dew of Hermon,</hi> it is <hi>bonum utile.</hi> Peace and plenty ever go together: Abundance of peace were not ſo fit a phraſe, if it were not to ſhew that abundance, is ever the effect, the fruit of peace. But Chriſt doth not only wiſh this, but alſo will it, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends it to them, and commands it them both under one, his teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was ever with au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hority.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Imperatively. Pax vobis,</hi> is as much as, <hi>Pacem babete in vohis:</hi> if it were not good for us, he would never wiſh it, much leſſe command it; and this here is but a remembring of them, ſaith Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> of what he had before ſo oft told them, of having peace one with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other. If his authority was doubted then; ſure it was ſufficiently confirmed now: now he was riſen from the dead, and had conque<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed all thoſe enemies of peace, even death it ſelf the laſt enemy of all. To ſpeak of peace, to adviſe to it, to enjoyn it was a very fit time: <hi>Dives</hi> in hell deſired no more, then that one ſhould riſe from the dead to teach his brethren.</p>
            <list>
               <label>Now the peace which commands us is</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Oris.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Operis.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Cordis.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. To ſpeak peace for ſtriſe, like to flames gather life by breath; angry words are ever heralds unto warre; they that will purſue peace
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:112137:6"/> muſt keep <hi>their tongue from evils, and their lips that they ſpake no guile:</hi> Curſes and reproaches are <hi>like arms of ſtraw to the fire of wrath,</hi> ſaith <hi>Camerarius,</hi> they adde fuell to it; but a <hi>ſoft anſwer,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layeth it. The Apoſtles though they had tongues given them like fire, yet they were ſuch as had light, as much as heat in them, and that heat which was, was cooled with a blaſt of winde, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. And heat can do no harm where it is governed by light; there muſt be <hi>habete poteſtatem in verbis,</hi> before there can be any hopes of <hi>habete pacem in vobis,</hi> they know not the way of peace, which know not how to do that.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The next is <hi>Pax operis,</hi> To practiſe, peace: Chriſt did both, they heard him ſpeak, and <hi>he ſhewed them his hands and his feet,</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm his practiſe, he was <hi>mighty in deed and in word:</hi> the Scripture places deed ever firſt where it ſpeaks of Chriſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 1. 1. <hi>Luke</hi> 24 19. to ſhew there was moſt worth in that; and Chriſts action ſhould be our imitation, when we ſpeak peace, we ſhould ſhew our hands that we practiſe it, that we labour for it, not <hi>Joa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and <hi>Judas</hi> like, have peace only in our mouth, but a ſword or ſtaffe in our hand: But it is poſſible our labour may be loſt, as <hi>Davids</hi> was in <hi>Pſal. 120. I labour for peace, but when I ſpeak unto them thereof, they make themſelves ready for battell.</hi> It is likely we ſhall ſpeed no better then Chriſt told his Diſciples, when as he ſent them forth with the like ſalutation, <hi>Pax buic domui:</hi> as it hits and meets with the Son of peace, ſo it will be retained, elſe returned back to us again; yet there muſt be ſtill</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Pax in corde,</hi> a well wiſhing unto peace, an hearty deſire of it; not to let enmity take up any room there, to expreſſe it by free motion of it, by glad receiving it, by ſeeking and ſuing for it, by ſending af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it and purchaſing it; till this be ſeen, we ſhew not our ſide, how it bleeds after peace: This is Chriſts wiſh, that we would do thus; and this is not only commended unto us, but commanded us: <hi>Pax vobis (i. e.) habete pacem in vobis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And let it now paſſe for an injunction, and not only for a ſaluta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Love is of the ſame nature with peace: our Saviour calls it a new Commandement, <hi>John</hi> 13. 34. Peace hath ſomewhat the advantage of that our Saviour ſpeaks of, and that only to <hi>Peter</hi> after his reſurrection, but this he gives in charge to all his Diſciples: <hi>Pax vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis,</hi> is he to them.</p>
            <p>We come to that now; the Perſons to whom it is enjoyned, his Diſciples; they were then gathered together, and their Congregation
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:112137:7"/> did fitly repreſent the Church of God; only they were gathered through fear, theſe through love: Now peace is never ſo fit as at a meeting, be it from what cauſe ſoever, whether of love or fear, there to be publiſhed, then to be entertained.</p>
            <p>When men are <hi>ſimul,</hi> there ought leaſt of all to be <hi>ſimultas:</hi> Peace is the <hi>Cartilage</hi> which keeps the members together, the bond of peace the Apoſtle calls it, becauſe the Church like a ſhea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, hath by it all her ears of corn kept from ſhattering together; This was the peace of Chriſts principall intendment, <hi>Pax Eccleſiae,</hi> that they ſhould alwaies be, as their bodies were conjoyned, ſo have their hearts and mindes united: as they are of one place, ſo have all one peace: we cannot ſay with any ſucceſſe, <hi>Pax huic domui,</hi> if they be not of one minde in the houſe.</p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Baſil</hi> reports with aſtoniſhment what he had by experience ſound in his travells, that when in all Arts and Sciences, and ſocieties, he ſaw peace and agreement: <hi>tantum in Eccleſiâ Chriſti pro quâ ipſe mortuus, maximum diſſidium, Aſcet. p.</hi> 186. He reckons it among the judgements of God, and we can do no leſſe, if any time we think ſeriouſly of it: he imputes the cauſe of that to mens contempt of their heavenly King, as <hi>Iſraels</hi> calamities in the time of Judges, becauſe every man did what they liſt, and there was no King in <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael;</hi> they which are rebells to the King will not be ruled by his Law, <hi>ſine Rege, &amp; ſine Lege</hi> ever go together; and they do little better but deny his ſoveraignty which reject his commands; they forgo their obedience, which caſt of his cognizance; nay with greater rage then the ſouldiers uſed him, they rent in ſunder his ſeamleſſe coat and break even his bones in peeces, ſo Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſpeaks of the Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick <hi>Donatus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There will be ever in the Church of God haters of Peace. The ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie of peace will be ſtill ſowing tares of diſſention, ever ſince the opening of the ſecond ſeal, <hi>Revel. 6. 4. There was power given to take peace from the earth:</hi> then was <hi>Pax terris,</hi> that part of the Angels ſong turned into <hi>vaeterris. Jehnes</hi> fury, and <hi>Jereboams</hi> ſchiſme carry all away before them: The Goſpel they pretend to both, as if it had gotten new colours, war and the ſword, and not peace, and love.</p>
            <p>Yet ſhall Chriſts wiſh take no effect: <hi>Pax vobis,</hi> will ſure be wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come to the Diſciples: <hi>Pax domui huic,</hi> to the ſons of peace here: Thoſe to whom Chriſt wiſheth it, are the ſame to whom the Angels proclaimed it, <hi>Luke 2. Pax terris,</hi> but <hi>quibus?</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Bernard:
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:112137:7"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> hominibus magnae ſcientiae, &amp; dignitatis, ſed bone voluntatis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what and if you will needs reject it? ſhall it be ſayd in vain, <hi>Pax vobis?</hi> if it finde no ſons of peace, it will return to vs again; the bleſſing of peace will be returned to them that plead for it: and that our Saviour pronounceth, <hi>bleſſed are the Peace makers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And bleſſed for ever, bleſſed be that Peacemaker who did not only plead for peace all his life, but purchaſed it by his death, who payd the priſe of it, his own bloud, who was not only the meſſenger of it, but the maker of it: and to ſhew that, <hi>he ſhewed them his hands and his ſide.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. I come to that now, the ſecond way of Chriſts being author of our peace, <hi>by mediation,</hi> by purchaſe; he ſayd; <hi>Peace be unto you and when he had ſo ſayd, he ſhewed them his hands and his ſide.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O hers were <hi>Evangelizantes pacem,</hi> the Angels from Heaven, the Apoſtles on earth; but <hi>procurantes pacem,</hi> none but he: they by mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration having received commiſſion from him, he only by mediation having his miſſion from the Father: they may be meſſengers, he only the maker, and in that reſpect he, and not they, is called <hi>Pax noſtra.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you require a ſign of it, there is the Prophet <hi>Jonabs</hi> in ſuch a ſtorm which would have ſoon ſwoopt up the ſhip and all her paſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers; Take me ſaith he, and caſt me into the ſea, and then the ſea ceaſed from her raging. <hi>Adam</hi> was the Carrick, in him all mankinde was imbarqued, and that was ready to be ſwallowed up in the Abyſſe of Gods high diſpleaſure: take me ſaith Chriſt, and let me paſſe through thoſe angry wounds; only with this difference, <hi>Jonahs</hi> truly ſayd it, <hi>Propter me haec tempeſtas;</hi> but of him ſaith <hi>Eſay, He was woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for our tranſgreſſions:</hi> and thoſe wounds which he then received, here he ſhewes unto his Diſciples: <hi>He ſhewed them his hands and his ſide.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Chriſt would have the wounds of his paſſion to be ſeen after his reſurrection, for many good reaſons. It is probable he hath them ſtill to ſhew: In a viſion which <hi>Zachary</hi> ſaw, 13. 6. there is one whether Saint or Angel, is bold to ask him, what are thoſe wounds in thy hands? and his anſwer is, Theſe are they which I received in the houſe of my friends. Saint <hi>Auſtine</hi> ſaith of the Martyrs, <hi>Omnes ſuas cicatrices in caelo habituros, non tanquam vitia ſed veritatis teſtimonia. de Civit. lib. 22. chap. 20. Not as arguments of their frailties, but as teſtimonies of their virtue. Among the reſt there are three not the leaſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:112137:8"/>1. To conſound his enemies when they ſhall look upon him whom they have pierced. <hi>Herod</hi> was affrighted when he heard of Chriſts works, and ſaid it is <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> whom I beheaded; even ſo ſhall they be daunted when they ſhall ſee his wounds, and ſay, it is Jeſus whom we crucified.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To confirm his friends: <hi>Ad ſananda infidelium cordium vulnera, ſervata clavorum &amp; lanceae veſtigia,</hi> ſaith <hi>Leo. Except I ſee</hi> (ſaith <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas) the print of his nayles, and put my hand into his ſide, I will not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve,</hi> verſe 25. <hi>&amp; vidit &amp; credidit:</hi> the mouthes of his wounds ſpake moſt effectually to his faith, he read beſt in the print of thoſe nayles, the reſurrection of his maſter. The report of Chriſts riſing, was as ſtrange to him, as to <hi>Jacob</hi> of <hi>Joſephs</hi> living, till he ſaw the wagons which <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſent for him, and <hi>Thomas</hi> the wounds which Jeſus ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered for him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That he might carry in his body the Trophees of his victory and our peace, ſaith <hi>Maldonate;</hi> that the wound in his ſide might be like the <hi>bow in the Cloud,</hi> the <hi>rainbow about the Throne,</hi> which <hi>John</hi> ſaw in his viſion, <hi>Revel.</hi> 4. 3. or like <hi>the bloud on the lentell, Exod.</hi> 12. or the <hi>red thred in the window, Joſhna</hi> 2. 18. that God when he ſees it, might remember his Covenant, that the godly might flie to his ſide as their ſanctuary, to the holes of that rock, to the ſecret place of the ſtairs of his Croſſe, and hide themſelves in that great and terrible day of the Lord. This was the purchaſe of his paſſion, a place to hide us in: there is no finding of any peace for us murtherers, out of theſe Cities of refuge; no way for us to happineſſe, but through theſe gates of the righteous, in at theſe everlaſting doors: Of the wounds of his ſide, may very truly be ſayd thoſe words of the Pſalmiſt, <hi>This is the gate of the Lord; the righteous ſhall enter in there at.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, he might well ſpeak of peace, which was made our peace, and wiſh us to peace which was wounded for it: Peace after warre is ever welcome, nay it is the honor of peace, that war is made for it. The em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleme of a ſouldier is a ſword in one hand, and fire in the other, with this motto, <hi>Sic quaerimus pacem,</hi> and it is Chriſts our Captains word, <hi>Veni quaerere &amp; ſanare;</hi> and war deſtroyes all, Peace only ſaveth.</p>
            <p>And now me thinks I hear thoſe wounds in his hands and ſide, like ſo many mouthes (for <hi>Quot vulnera, tot ora)</hi> ſaying unto you, <hi>Peace be unto you; Videte quantum conſtitit mihi pax veſtra,</hi> put your fingers here and ſee mine hands, put forth your hands here, and put them into my ſide; make not my wounds greater by your infidelity,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:112137:8"/> then the Jewes did with all their cruelty; will you not beleeve ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept you ſee them bleed afreſh in my members, in my ſpouſe the Church? can you ſlight that for which I payd ſo dear? prize you my bloud at ſo low a rate, that upon ſuch ſlight occaſions you contemne the purchaſe of it; will you ſell me again for thirty pence, and cry out ſo many <hi>crucifies,</hi> rather then put up any little injurie? Can you for a ceremony caſhiere all your charity, and ſo readily break the bond of peace; for which I was content to be bound over to inſupportable pains? will you uſe me more deſpightfully then thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urriſh Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers did? they neither rent my garments, nor brake my bones, and will you tear in peeces that ſeamleſſe coat of charity, in which I have put my Spouſe; as if you were wilde beaſts? and like fierce Tygers, make wide wounds in my body which is the Church? Had I never bought it for you, or being bought, had I never brought it to you, you could not have been more ſtrangely careleſſe of it. All I can ſay unto you, is <hi>Peace be unto you;</hi> theſe wounds in my hands and ſide will ſay more, and <hi>he ſhewed them his hands and his ſide.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And it will make you think the better of peace whiles you live, if you conſider one thing more, whoſe hands they are which deliver it unto you; if there were any better thing in the world, thoſe hands would not have kept it from you; that ſide would have afforded bloud ſufficient enough to have procured it for you; and you may be ſure it is worth the receiving which Chriſt gives you, you ought not to refuſe that which he bought at ſo dear a price.</p>
            <p>I would here winde up all, leſt while I be a factor for your peace, by too much tediouſneſſe I forfeit mine own; but that in Chriſts ſhewing his hands and his ſide, after he ſaid, <hi>Peace be unto you;</hi> is as me thinks imported ſomething of a morall intendment. Saint <hi>Luke</hi> ſaith, they were his hands and his feet; it is likely he ſhewed them all. 1. His ſide, how it deſired their peace. 2. His hands and his feet, how they laboured for it.</p>
            <p>In this ſenſe we are to imitate him, the words of our commiſſion are the ſame with his; <hi>Pax vobis,</hi> and <hi>Pax. buic Domni</hi> are much at one; and himſelf ſaith, <hi>ſicut miſit me Pater, &amp;c.</hi> We cannot ſhew you our ſide how it hath bled for it; our hands and feet how they were wounded for it, that only Chriſt can do, and thoſe wounds he hath yet to ſhew; yet in a morall meaning, we ſhew you our ſide, how earneſtly we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire it, our hands and our feet, how we labour for it. Elſe</p>
            <p>The voice of peace, if the heart be not to wiſh it, the hands to work
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:112137:9"/> it, will do little good; thoſe which come with it on that faſhion, art but like the bramble in <hi>Jothams</hi> parable, <hi>Judges</hi> 9. 15. which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed peace to thoſe that truſt on him; and is likely firſt to ſcratch them that lay hold on it: Though one once carried away the bleſſing from old <hi>Iſaac,</hi> I no where finde any ever brought it, which came with the voice of <hi>Jacob,</hi> and the hands of <hi>Eſau.</hi> The Scripture joyns <hi>ſalt</hi> and <hi>peace</hi> together, <hi>habete ſalem &amp; pacem, Mark</hi> 9. 50. and that is <hi>ſal ſcientiae &amp; conſcientiae,</hi> which are matters of the heart and hands, and not meerly of the tongue. Indeed they muſt be all three ſeaſoned, our words, our wiſhes, our works; before <hi>habete ſalme,</hi> there will be no <hi>habete Pacem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How ever, let thoſe which are <hi>ſal Terrae,</hi> not loſe their ſeaſon: let their feet be ſhod with the preparations of the Goſpel of peace, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6. 15. and that preparation is eſpecially in patient putting up of wrongs: There is no true way of peace to be had there without it. And then will others ſay; <hi>Quare ſpeciofi ſunt pedes Evangelizantium pacem?</hi> their feet muſt be ſeen in the wayes of Peace, as well as well as their voices heard, with the words of peace; it is no right comming to come with the voice of a Turtle, and the talon of an Harpie. To ſuch as you are Chriſt eſpecially commends peace, in <hi>Pax vobis,</hi> and commands it too, <hi>in Pacem habete in vobis:</hi> do you pray for peace, and plead for it, and practice it, be benefactours for peace, that you may one day receive the bleſſing of peace.</p>
            <p>And now <hi>Pax vobis,</hi> to you all; I promiſed you to end as I began, <hi>Pece be unto you.</hi> Chriſt wiſheth it to you, and adviſeth you to it: you can do no leſſe then return him praiſe for it, Glory unto Heaven, for peace on earth. The Angels taught us that way in their hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Hymne; and there is no way like that to keep peace here, than by giving glory there. Unto him ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the ligheſt Heavens, who is the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor and giver of Peace, be given all Glory, and praiſe, now and ever, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:112137:9"/>
            <head>THE SECOND SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>LAMENT. 5. 16.</bibl>
               <q>Woe now unto us, That we have ſinn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>HEre is <hi>Flebile principium,</hi> a lamentable beginning: This Text comes like man himſelf into the world, crying; you could not look that this day ſhould bring forth any other childe, then a childe of ſorrow: <hi>Ben-onies</hi> are ever the fruits of true faſts: If the day it ſelf could ſpeak. you ſhould have no other voyce from it then that which <hi>Iſaiab</hi> heard: A voyce ſaying, <hi>Cry, Iſai.</hi> 40. 6. Now if you ask with him, what ſhall I cry, my Text will direct you in that; <hi>Woe now unto us, that we have ſinned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here is a cry to be taken up by all of us; and there is good reaſon for it. There have been divers cryes already, only we our ſelves have not cryed, God himſelf hath cryed in the <hi>Proverbs, Chap. 1. Verſe 20. Turn you at my correction:</hi> His Miniſters have cryed, and never left crying, <hi>Iſaiab, Jeremy,</hi> and <hi>Jonab;</hi> our ſinnes have alſo cryed, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto heaven hath their cry aſcended,</hi> it hath come unto the ears of the Almighty; Judgement alſo hath begun to cry, and her voyce to be exalted above mercy; only we, as if we were ſenſeleſſe, have ſtood ſtill at this time, and not cryed at all: But now we do begin, and it is well thought on, before we come into the cry of <hi>Egypt,</hi> a cry of midnight, <hi>we dye all, Exod.</hi> 12. 33. Or that diſmall cry which ſhall be in the laſt night of all, a crying <hi>to the rocks to hide us, and the mountains to fall upon us.</hi> The way not to cry then, will be to cry now: to make our ſelves cry before we be made to cry; the cryes of repentance prevent the cryes of vengeance, eſpecially when we joyn all of us in this cry. It hath been reported, that the cry of an huge Army hath intercepted the flight of Birds, they have not been able to paſſe over for it, but have fallen down in the midſt: ſo are Gods flying Judgements to be intercepted: if we cry all of us, as
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:112137:10"/> we are appointed. I will only adde that advice of a King concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this crying, and at ſuch a time as this was: that it may be a ſtrong cry, Let us <hi>cry mightily unto God, Jon.</hi> 3. 8.</p>
            <p>But are we to cry indeed? me thinks that were fitteſt to be done in ſecret; tears ſhed in private, are commonly the tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt; <hi>Ille dolet verè qui ſine teſte dolet,</hi> they ſpeak loudeſt which make leaſt noiſe; this is to be done, and done often by us: Yet we are to do it in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique too; to weep with them that weep, was ever held ſeaſonable, eſpecially when there is a juſt cauſe of weeping as now there is; it will be an unanſwerable fault, if the Church ſhall have juſt cauſe to complain of us, <hi>We have mourned unto you, and you have not wept.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here we are not as upon a ſtage, only to perſonate a crying; we muſt act our own parts; like him which was to act a lament<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble part, that he might do it the better, call to remembrance the death of his only ſonne, whom he moſt dearly loved, and fell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed into true tears; none of us but have cauſe enough, if we but call it unto minde, to make us to weep, if not for others ſins, yet for our own; <hi>hinc illae lachrimae.</hi> They, they alone are a ſufficient motive to make our hearts ſeek vent at our tongues, to make uſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y at leaſt thus much, <hi>Woe unto us, that we have ſinned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We ſhould not need this adoe, if we were but of <hi>Davids,</hi> or <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,</hi> or <hi>Peters,</hi> or <hi>Mary Magdalens</hi> temper, apt to cry: they could <hi>water their Beds, and mingle their drink with their tears;</hi> The Poets fain that <hi>Prometheus,</hi> when he made man, tempered his clay with tears; and yet how hardly come they from us, as if our natures were of another mould? I muſt needs grant a Corporall Calamity hath f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tcht too many our of ſome, even to a prejudicating of their faith, but when hath a ſpirituall done the like? is nature ſuch an enemy to the ſoul, that the can be prodigall of her tears, when any temporall affliction moves her, and ſo baſe and nigardly, when a ſpirituall afflicts her? Woe is me that I have not <hi>Moſes</hi> rod, to ſtrike theſe Rocks; I have not the art to make you weep, no not to weep my ſelf. The Angel of God deſcend this day, and ſtir our pools; he touch our hearts, that they may teach our eyes true tears, and our t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ngu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s ſtrong cryes, that we may with unfained ſorrow ſay, though it be but the words of this Text: <hi>Woe now unto us, that me have ſinned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I might have fitted you with a Text of more words, but not of more matter: long ſpeeches are not alwayes ſtrong ones: <hi>Magnum</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:112137:10"/> 
               <hi>in parvo,</hi> is natures beſt work, ſo it is reaſons, ſo it is religions: Thoſe which are run out in length have commonly leaſt ſpirits in them. How ſhort was <hi>Moſes</hi> cry, yet how forceable? Nay, when he had ſaid leaſt, he ſpake loudeſt, <hi>Exod.</hi> 14. 45. our Saviours cryes are by the Apoſtle called ſtrong, yet they were long none of them: how ſhort is that which he hath taught us to utter, and yet not the leſſe effectuall? how powerfull was the Publican in that ſhort petition, <hi>God he mercifull to me a ſinner?</hi> The Phariſee ſaid more, but went home with leſſe. There are but three ſyllables in <hi>peccavi,</hi> yet <hi>quantum valent,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Ambroſe. David</hi> received pardon only for them: it is but little we are to ſay now, we may ſay it in a moment, if we ſay it right; and that we may do that, we muſt ſay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of the manner of ſaying it.</p>
            <p>If you pleaſe but to obſerve the Text where it is placed, you will finde two neceſſary attendants on it: The Book is a <hi>Lamentation,</hi> the Chapter a Petition; it is as <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> ſaid of himſelf, when he ſate between <hi>Horace</hi> and <hi>Virgil, inter ſuſpiria &amp; lachrimas:</hi> The Author of it was a Petitioner with tears in his eyes, he was like <hi>a Dove upon the Rivers of waters, Can.</hi> 5. 12. His heart mourning, his head dropping: prayers and tears, are the true acconts of his voyce, he ſpake with his eyes, aſwell as with his tongue: Lamentations, mourning, and woe are not ſevered, they are joyned by <hi>Ezekiel</hi> in Gods Book, they are not parted by <hi>Jeremy</hi> in his: ſo it is the manner of repentance to aſſume what is due by vengeance, ſhe doth freely undergoe whatſoever juſtice doth award: they belong to her by her own judgement, whatſoever is due by Gods: So ſhe uſeth to judge her ſelf before hand: This is her manner, and to be practiſed by us now, with Lamentation, and mourning, to pronounce our woe. <hi>Woe now unto us, that we have ſinned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I may well tearm my Text, the lamentation of a ſinner, or rather the lamentation of ſinners, for we are not in our private Cloſets now; the time hath made it publique, we are to joyn all of us in doing of it, ſo the Text takes us in all, it is not to be ſaid by one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, but by many, all of us that are hear preſent: <hi>Woe now unto us, that we have ſinned.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <label>Now in ſaying this, we ſay two things,</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. Our miſery, which is the cauſe of our Lamentatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>Woe now unto us.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. Our ſin, which is the cauſe of our miſery, <hi>That we have ſinned.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:112137:11"/>
            <p>We begin with the firſt, the ſence of our miſery, and that will bring us afterwards to a ſight of our ſin; and in that we have two things to be conſidered.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, The greatneſſe of it.</item>
               <item>Secondly, The neerneſſe of it.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt the greatneſſe of it, it is expreſſed in one word, but that the moſt ſignificant, and full that can be, if any expreſſion may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite, and take in all the intentions of miſery, that is it, <hi>Woe now unto us,</hi> it is in that word <hi>Woe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>condly, the neerneſſe of it for miſeries a farre of, do not ſo much affect our ſences, we are not ſo much touched with them, as to go about to prevent them It was S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Iohns</hi> wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r, <hi>Quit vos prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nonuit fugere ab irâ venturâ,</hi> that any ſhould take ſo much thought as to think of that: But this is neer two wayes: Firſt, in reſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ct of perſons, it is our own and not others. Secondly, of time, it is not to come, but is come already. <hi>Woe now unto us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And by that time we have conſidered theſe we ſhall finde cauſe enough for lamentation, and finding th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe off<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cts, look further to the true cauſe of our miſery, which is our ſin, take a full ſight of that, and that is properly <hi>opus Diei;</hi> I humbly beg of God his aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, while I diſpatch it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Our Miſery. That takes up the firſt place: So it uſeth in all complaints, eſpecially where our pain is as it is heer, <hi>Woe</hi> is the wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, we have it expreſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d by;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Woe,</hi> is a word of malediction and commination, there i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and a threatning <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ver imployed in that: any mean Gramma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian knows the meaning of that interj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ction. Two wayes only do we finde it uſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d in Scripture. 1. By God, when he denouncethany judgement upon others: So it is often in the Prophets, <hi>Iſai. 5. Ezek.</hi> 13. and by our Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iour in the Evangeliſts, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23. by the Angel in the <hi>Apocalips,</hi> Chap. 18. and Chap. 9. 2. By others when they lament any judgement already fallen, or likely to fall upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, in <hi>Ieremy</hi> we fin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e it often, <hi>Iere. 4. 31. Woe is me now, for my ſoul fainteth, Iere. 10. 19. Woe is me for my deſtruction, and my grievous plague, Iere. 15. 10. Woe is me my Mother, that thou baſt born me a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions man, a man that ſtriveth with the whole earth:</hi> Of this ſence is this Text: we do even curſe our ſelves in ſaying of it, at leaſt we make application of that curſe which doth belo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g unto us.</p>
            <p>And this is very proper to this time, we are now in hand with
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:112137:11"/> that w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> the Apoſtle elſe where adviſeth us unto, <hi>To judge our ſelves, that we may not be judged of the Lord,</hi> by denouncing of a curſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, we take upon us to be Judges; in the Court of Conſcience, we are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to do it to our ſelves; it is the part of the diſcipline of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, to award that unto our ſelves, which the Juſtic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of God hath threatned unto ſinners; ſuch we are; nay the very cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>feſt of ſinners: we do not do it poteſtative, but approbative, we conſent that the judgement of God is juſt: and we cannot ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> doth belong unto us then this; this is the leaſt that we can ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge, <hi>Woe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us.</hi> Now repentance is rightly called by the School a pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce of ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tice, it conſiſts eſpecially in awarding due puniſhment: <hi>poeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia à puniendo,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Maſter,</hi> L. 4. d. 14. We are apt in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to follow <hi>Peters</hi> counſell, <hi>Maſter favour thy ſelf:</hi> either we ſee not fully what we have committed, that part of the wallet we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly caſt behinde, or we are but partiall judges to determine what we have deſerved: but true repentance may not ſo ſpare her ſelf; ſhe is to aſſigne all that doth belong unto her ſelf, to appoint in her own judgement, whatſoever divin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> judgement hath threatned.</p>
            <p>And then once <hi>Woe</hi> will be too little, we finde it thrice threatned <hi>Revel. 8. 13. Woe, woe, woe,</hi> and when theſe are paſt with S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Bernard,</hi> we ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l finde a fourth, it will be but injuſtice with the King of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to ſmite but thrice, when we ſhould do it five or ſixe times, it will be but to repeat the words ſo much the oftner, and four woes we ſhall in juſtice award unto our ſelves, and thoſe four, from four places. Firſt, From Heaven above us. Secondly, From the world without us. Thirdly, From our own conſciences within us. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, From hell beneath us; in reſpect of every one of theſe, we have juſt cauſe to ſay, <hi>Woe now unto us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. From heaven above us.] <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hen we do contemplate the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and power of an incenſed Judge, how the Lord of H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſts is up in armes againſt us, how juſtice muſters up her clouds, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d winds, and ſtormes; how <hi>thouſand thouſands, and ten thouſand thouſands, Dan.</hi> 7. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ily march in his Army; how he cometh with flames of fire, rendring of vengeance; how with him Judgement cannot be prevaricated; no bribes will blinde his eyes; no friends corrupt his affections; mercy dares not plead; tears will not be heard to ſpeak; who is able to ſtand before conſuming fire; who can dwell with everlaſting burnings? How the very <hi>Earth ſhall melt at his preſence</hi> and the <hi>heavens be rowled up, as in a ſcrowle before him;</hi> how he will
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:112137:12"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ip up the bowels of the heart it ſelf, and ſearch the ſecrets of the ſoul; how he found not ſtedfaſtneſſe in his Angels, and even the Starres are unclean in his ſight: How much more is man a worm, even the Son of man, which is but a worm? If <hi>Moſes</hi> could not abide his back parts, how ſhall we endure his preſence? what can we conclude from this contemplation, but with my Text, <hi>Woe is unto us?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. One woe is paſt, but behold a ſecond: If heaven do abandon us, how ſhall the Earth comfort us? If the Lord be againſt us, how can I help? was ſaid by a King, one as likely to help, as any in the world. We may well look about us, but we ſhall finde with <hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,</hi> our <hi>plague is deſperate, our wound is incurable:</hi> When God is angry, he infatuates even counſells, <hi>quos perdere vult dementat.</hi> He mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s abortive all policies; you may learn it by <hi>Achitophels;</hi> he ſuffers the Prophets themſelves to provelyers, as they did in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading <hi>Abab</hi> to battail: he turns the ſwords of Armies againſt themſelves, and their bows into their own bowels; he makes them bring in a ſtrong people, to ſcourge themſelves, as <hi>Iſrael</hi> the <hi>Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> as children their own rod. He ſmites them <hi>with blindneſſe, and aſtoniſhment,</hi> as he threatned <hi>Iſrael, Deut.</hi> 28. 28. If we look to the Church, we finde giddyneſſe; to the Common-weal madneſſe; if without us to the North, <hi>vae malum,</hi> there is a miſt; to the South there ever and anon ariſeth a cloud, threatning a ſtorm; if within us, we may ſay with the Apoſtle, we are in <hi>perils by falſe Brethren;</hi> there are Vipers which will eate up the bowels of the Mother that bred them; treaſons, and conſpiracies fill us with fears; diviſions, and diſtractions adde unto our woes: The world is by <hi>Plato</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to a ſhop, almoſt whatſoever we look upon, we may ſay with the buyer in <hi>Solomon, malum eſt, malum eſt,</hi> it is naught, it is naught. We have cauſe enough, if we conſider it, to ſay the ſecond time, <hi>Woe is now unto us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. And yet behold a third, though there be never ſo many trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, without us; yet peace within us, would afford us comfort: but let us look within us, and aske, is it peace? <hi>There is no peace unto the wicked,</hi> our own conſciences will tell us that; They are wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes to accuſe us of ſin, and judges to condemne us to woe. If they be quiet and trouble us not, our woe is the greater, becauſe our conſciences are ſecure; but if troubleſome, how great is our woe! They are the Books by which we ſhall be judged hereafter: nay,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:112137:12"/> by them we may become our own judges now. Search and ſee if in our own judgement, we may not pronounce againſt our ſelves another woe: how unſufferable are their checks; how evident their accuſations; how faithfull their records: others cannot read them, and may judge us better then we are; we which know them our ſelves, if we will deal truly, muſt needs pronource a righteous judgement, and that is; <hi>Woe be unto us, becauſe we have ſinned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Three woes are paſt, but behold a fourth. It is S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Bernards</hi> woe, of his adding; if we look below us, we ſhall have cauſe to ſay it, and there we ſhall finde the complement of all woe: can you endure to hear that fearfull ſentence, depart you curſed, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſaying, <hi>Woe be unto us?</hi> how ready is the cruell executioner of ſouls, the devill, to hale us thither? how wide hath hell opened her mouth to receive us there? could we but hear the diſmall groans, and yelling cryes which they make, that are ſwallowed up into the river of Brimſtone; Let <hi>Dives</hi> ſpeak for the reſt of his fellows, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, I am grievouſly tormented; did we but beleeve the woefull extremity which they are in, that are in utter darkneſſe. Let our Saviours report work it into our faith, it is weeping, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d wailing, and gnaſhing of teeth; night the duration of it not paſſe for a fable; we have the everlaſting Truth to confirme it, there <hi>the worm dyeth not, and the fire is not quenched:</hi> have we not ſufficient cauſe to cry out, <hi>Woe be unto us?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How ſhall I make you ſay it, if this will not? hither we are judged, if our judgement be right: we muſt not favour our ſelves and ſay, this ſhall not be unto us: repentance cannot be true if par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall: we muſt thus judge our ſelves, that we may not be judged, <hi>non ſumus bis judicandi,</hi> ſaith S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Bernard:</hi> God will ſpare us, if we ſpare not our ſelves. Let us caſt our ſelves down at the footſtool of his judgement Seat, and confeſſe what we have deſerved; Let us come as <hi>Benbadads</hi> ſervants did to the King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> with Sack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth about our loynes, and ropes about our heads, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 20. 32. ſuch coming becomes us beſt this day; Let us caſt our ſelves out of heaven, as expecting only wrath from thence; out of the world, as finding only miſeries there; out of our ſelves, as feeling nothing but terrours there; down even to hell it ſelf, whether we deſerve to be for ever plunged; Let groans fill our ſouls, and tears our eyes, <hi>vae vohis qui ridetis,</hi> in ſuch a day as this is; and let our mouths be filled with cryes, ſaying it often; <hi>Woe now unto us, that we have ſinned.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:112137:13"/>
            <p>But, If the greatneſſe of our miſery have not ſufficiently brought us to that; yet the neerneſſe of it, will work ſome true effects. Things a farre of, work upon our apprehenſion ſomewhat, but not much upon our paſſion; but paſſion muſt be ſet to work now; this day is the paſſion day of repentance. In two reſpects we ſhall finde it neer enough. 1. Of Perſon. 2. Of Time. Thoſe two will ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſufficiently to the greatneſſe of our miſery, we ſhall not be put to in quire further.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Of Perſon, it is our own miſery; it belongs to our ſelves: <hi>Woe now to us.</hi> Others miſeries affect us not much, they work ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their diſtance, of place, or perſon, <hi>Pacis cum proximus ardet,</hi> there begins our perplexity. When our ſelves come to be touched, and repentance toucheth no where elſe, it ſwells in her own bancks, it keepeth ſeſſions at home, and paſleth judgement only againſt it ſelf; We, we are the men, to whom woe doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertain; <hi>noſtra res agitur,</hi> we muſt not put it of from our ſelves, leaſt God I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y it on: <hi>To us belongeth ſhame and confuſion of face,</hi> ſaith <hi>Daniel, Dan.</hi> 9. repentance threatens none but it ſelf, <hi>vae nobis,</hi> is the voice of it: <hi>Woe unto us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Of Time Neither doth it deferre its iudgement, nor put of the evill day farre from us, we deſerve to have it brought upon us preſently, and repentance iudgeth according to our deſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rts. Woe <hi>now</hi> unto us: now indeed were it iuſtice with God, to bring upon us all this woe, he hath forborne and given u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> many times of try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, but we have deſpiſed the riches of his grace, and his goodneſſe hath not lead us to repentance. He hath come theſe many yeers, looking for fruit, and found nothing but leaves; <hi>now</hi> might he in iuſtice lay his Axe to our roote, and bid cut us down; <hi>now</hi> might he pronounce a curſe againſt us, and make us wither away; he might <hi>now</hi> ſpeak unto us in his diſpleaſure, depart you curſed, and powre upon us all his ſtorms of indignation and vengeance. If we were now to ſtand before Gods tribunall, and to be indged according to our deſerts, and there we are now placed by repentance; even now preſently, were all this miſery to come upon us.</p>
            <p>Now if any thing will work true appr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>henſion in us, it muſt be this: <hi>Iraventura.</hi> Makes not any deep impreſſion in many of us: the day of death, though we ſee it a farre of, may ſtrike us into ſo ne dumps; but they are never ſo true as—<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Cum ſit inbeforae ſimilis, jam jamque tenere.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:112137:13"/>
            <p>When we ſee an hand writing with <hi>Baltazer,</hi> or hear a voyce ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our doom with <hi>Nabuch adnezzar,</hi> then will our <hi>joynts he looſed,</hi> and our <hi>knees tremble:</hi> Saint <hi>Gregory</hi> reports it of himſelf, that when he expounded that ſentence of <hi>Abraham</hi> unto <hi>Dives, now thou art tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented,</hi> he was not able to on in his Sermon. <hi>Pavore potius indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent quam expoſitione,</hi> ſaith he, to his Auditors; the apprehenſion of the preſent, wrought ſo much upon him, as if the <hi>jam vero,</hi> were <hi>iam verum,</hi> now to be ſaid to any of us, as it was to him; indeed we are to ſay it our ſelves now, Woe <hi>now</hi> unto us: This certainly will make us ſufficiently apprehenſive of our miſery.</p>
            <p>And now as men brought unto ſome dangerous diſeaſe, ever look unto the cauſe that brought them to it, being in a ſtorm as <hi>Jonahs</hi> Marriners were, they caſt about to finde the fountain of it: it is the great conſultation of this Kingdom at this time, to finde out the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of thoſe great diſtempers that are in it: So the ſence of our mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery will bring us to a ſight of our ſin, for indeed <hi>hinc illae lachrimae;</hi> all our ſorrows come from thence, we muſt lay all our fault upon our ſins, our ſins are the <hi>troublers of ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Iſrael,</hi> and that leads me to the ſecond part of my Text. <hi>Woe now unto us, that we have ſinned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We came not till now to the cry of true repentance; it is not her miſery ſhe is under, but the ſin ſhe hath committed makes her cry: it is all the note that they have in hell, <hi>Woe now unto us;</hi> but they never come to ſay that we have ſinned; for there is no place for repentance, the ſence of their miſeries makes them only cry, not any ſorrow or remorſe for their ſins: But it is theſe we muſt now cry of; if we be true penitents, our ſins muſt trouble us, and not any other troubles whatſoever.</p>
            <p>And now it is fitteſt to be troubled for them, for in times of other afflictions, we cannot ſo well ſpend our tears upon our ſins; torments of the body, will drink up our ſpirits, the pains which we endure, take up our complaints, our ſins are not ſo well thought on, when our ſences are otherwiſe perplexed; ſorrow often proves too late, which is let alone till then; but now we do but make our ſelves mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, we willingly aſſume woe unto our ſelves, thoſe woes we ſpake of (we bleſſe the goodneſſe, and long ſuffering of our God) are not as yet forced upon us, but freely aſſumed by us; other ſorrows go not ſo neer unto our hearts at this time, that there may be the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter room for the ſorrow, for our ſins; ſins are beſt lamented, when we are otherwiſe well, and not afflicted: <hi>Pharoah</hi> and <hi>Abab</hi> have done
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:112137:14"/> it in extremity, but it came not freely from them, but by force; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides they lamented their plagues, not their ſins: But it is for theſe that we are troubled; not that we are puniſhed, but that we have ſinned.</p>
            <p>And that we may thoroughly be troubled for them, we muſt be ſure to take a good ſight of them; not cover them as <hi>Cain,</hi> nor hide them as <hi>Adam;</hi> not caſt them behinde our backs, but bring them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us, ſet them in our ſight, that God may cover them, while we diſcover them, that when we bring them before our faces, he may caſt them behinde his back: Sin cannot be hid, but when God hides it, we may rake it up, as we do fire in embers, but at the day of Revelation, God will bring it to light.</p>
            <p>But then to ſay that we have ſinned, will not be enough to make us ſee our ſins; we have ſpent enough in the commiſſion, Saint <hi>Peter</hi> tells us; ſhall we be ſhort in our confeſſion? If we did go about it, we could not bring all our ſins to our remembrance: Holy men though they have ſtudied the Art of Arithmetike, have fain to ſet down at the foot of their accompt, an indefinite number; <hi>my ſins are more then the hairs of my bead,</hi> ſaith <hi>David, then the ſands on the Sea ſhore, then the ſtars in the firmament.</hi> Our ſecret ſins, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Bernard</hi> cals them, <hi>maris magni rep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilia,</hi> they are like the creeping creatures of the great Sea, innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: yet as an huge army, though the common ſouldiers be not to be muſtered, the heads and chieftains are: in the firmament the ſtarres are not to be numbred, yet thoſe of greateſt influence, and magnitude are: among our ſins there are leaders, Captains over their hundreds, and thouſands; there are ſome of more tranſcendent magnitude, and maligne influence; we may take ſight of them, and we ſhall not tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe the limits of the Text neither; it is to ſay, but ſo much the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; <hi>that we have ſinned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We begin with <hi>Pride,</hi> that <hi>Primum pec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atorum,</hi> as <hi>Syrach</hi> calls it; a ſin which firſt began in heaven, and tumbled the firſt abetters of it down to hell; That Epidemicall ſin which hath infected the race of all mankinde; and like a moſt malignant diſeaſe runs thorough all his veines, from that man of ſin, <hi>the King of all the children of Pride,</hi> as <hi>Job</hi> terms the <hi>Leviathan, who hath the horns of the Lamb, but the mouth of the Dragon, with which he ſpeaketh proud words.</hi> Unto the loweſt ſinner amongſt the ſonnes of men, is this peſtilence diſperſed: thoſe which have ſeemed moſt to trample upon pride, and made pretences of voluntary humility, have done it with greater pride, as <hi>Plato</hi> ſaid
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:112137:14"/> of <hi>Diogenes,</hi> when he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ord upon his chair with greater Pride, then ever he ſate in it: greater pride below often goes about to pull down leſſer pride above; I muſt not ſtand to tell you what the pride of our ſelf conceit is, the magnifying of our ſelves, the deſpiſing of our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, our high looks, and proud ſtomacks, the heighth of our apparell, the glory of our Pompe, how we perch up to the higheſt twig of our eſtate, till the boughs will not bear us, how we look down like the ſonnes of <hi>Anack,</hi> upon our brethren as Graſhoppers; how full every vain of us is of this vice, it is enough to ſee it, and to ſay, <hi>Woe now un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, that we have ſinned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next ſin is <hi>covetouſneſſe, Amor ſceleratus habendi, the root of all evill,</hi> as the Apoſtle calls, becauſe it gives nouriſhment and groweth to all other ſins; even pride it ſelf hath grown up by it, Idolatry, Prophanation, Sacriledge, Extortion, and infinite others, are troupers in this band: the love of <hi>Mammon</hi> hath begotten it, the wages of <hi>Balaam,</hi> and the booty of <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bazi,</hi> and the Vineyard of <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>both</hi> have maintained it. This alſo is our ſin, <hi>and woe is unto us, that we have ſinned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe two, Pride and Coveteouſneſſe, have their reſidence in the heart, have uſurped Gods manſion, and left him no room there; But</p>
            <p>The third ſin is <hi>Swearing,</hi> which is a cankar in the mouth, an open Sepulcher in the throat, a ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ink that doth aſcend to heaven, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects the ſacred name of God, the true Generall of Blaſphemies; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries, lyings, &amp;c. It is a ſin which crucifies Chriſt a new, and tears his very wounds and body in peeces, and ſheds his pretious bloud a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, a ſin which never goes without a curſe a long with it, which the jealous God will not let go unrevenged. This alſo is our ſin, <hi>and woe is unto us, that we have ſinned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will but name another, a capitall ſin among the Armies of <hi>Lucifer,</hi> it is Drunkenneſſe the ring leader to adulteries, quarrels, wounds, diſtempers, to profanneſſe, uncharitableneſſe: ſwearing flyes into the face of God, but drunkenneſſe defaces the image of God; he is the ſepulcher of the creatures of God, nay he is his own ſepulcher, being entombed in his own bowels; It is a ſin which began with the new world, and hath been cryed down by the Prophets, Apoſtles, Fathers, Paſtors of the Church, and yet they have not prevailed; it is a crying ſin which maketh a loud noiſe in Gods ears; and it is our ſin alſo, <hi>woe now unto us, that we have ſinned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have named theſe four, becauſe of the four woes we ſpake of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore;
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:112137:15"/> and indeed if you peruſe but the fifth chapter of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> you ſhall finde a ſeverall woe threatned to each of them. I muſt not go about to number the reſt, I cannot do it, I muſt ſay with the <hi>Pſalmiſt, Oh how great is the ſumme of them!</hi> and ſet that at the foot of the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt; I can ſhew you but a part of this great Army, as <hi>Balack</hi> ſhewed <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>laam,</hi> but let that be enough to make you curſe them all, and ſay, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> unto us, that we have ſinned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us not now put them off, and ſay, theſe are indeed the ſins of the times; with <hi>Saul, the people have ſinned<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Juſtus eſt accuſator ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> true repentance accuſeth none but it ſelf; <hi>I have ſinned,</hi> ſaith <hi>David. we have ſinned, we have done wickedly,</hi> ſaith <hi>Daniel.</hi> We our ſelves are the men, <hi>me, me, adſum qui fici, in me convertite flaminat;</hi> they are our ſine that have troubled <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſay it, though to the ſhame of our faces: <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ertul.</note> Let not us be <hi>ad delinquendum expandentes frontem, ad deprecandum ſubducenter;</hi> Let us ſay it, and give God glory by our ſaying it, as <hi>Joſhnah</hi> taught <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>han,</hi> but to our own ſhame, and the conſuſion of our faces; <hi>Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> woe now unto us, that we have ſinned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ile give you one obſervation more from the Text, <hi>woe now unto us;</hi> the pain, that is preſent, ſo we are to judge, ſo it would be i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that great Judge of all do not forbear us: but the ſin: that is paſt, the pleaſure that was in it, that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> gone; that we have ſinned, this is ever the ſting of ſin. The fruit that it brings forth, is ſhame, the reward it leaves behinde is death; all the worth of it is woe. <hi>Woe now unto us, that we have ſinnod.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What remains now, but that the ſence of our miſery, and the ſight <note place="margin">Exod. 31. 31.</note> of our ſins like, <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ton</hi> and <hi>Hur</hi> make us, <hi>bold up our hands, with Moſes unto God in crying?</hi> That ceremony is not out of ſeaſon now, it is all that remains, and let us cry a great and a ſtrong cry unto God, ſaying: O Lord we have ſinned a grievous ſin, therefore if thou pardon our ſin, thy mercy ſhall appear: and let us withall beleeve aſſuredly, that for the ſtrong crying of his ſonne, he will hear our faithfull, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fained, though but weak, and feeble cryes; for his ſatisfaction which be once made, he will forgive our ſins, and accept of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance. To whom with the Father, and the holy Ghoſt, three Perſons, but one God, bleſſed for ever, be all praiſe and glory, now, and ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="sermon">
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:112137:15"/>
            <head>THE THIRD SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>1 COR 10. 16, 17.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>The Cup of bleſſing which we bleſſe, is it not the Communion of the bloud of Chriſt? the bread which we breake, is it not the Communion of the body of Chriſt?</p>
                  <p>17. For we that are many, are one bread and one body, becauſe we are partakers of one bread.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THeſe words are an argument of the Apoſtle, and ſuch an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, taken <hi>ab axiomate conceſſo,</hi> againſt which there could be no diſputing: he appeals to themſelves <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which were able to judge of the truth of it; and if to judge, then to contradict it if not true.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Two things are to be taken notice of about it. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. The Cohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. The Inference; the cauſe of it, and the caſe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt is the point of Idolatry, from which he diſwades his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians, verſe 14. <hi>My beloved, flee from Idolatry, for</hi> Idolaters have <hi>fellowſhip with Divels;</hi> and I would not have you which <hi>drink of the Cup of the Lord, drink of the cup of divels;</hi> which are <hi>partakers of the Lords table,</hi> be <hi>partakers of the table of divels,</hi> verſe 20, 21. Neither indeed can there be any communion between Chriſt and Belial: now they might poſſibly except; Though they did eat of things ſacrificed to Idols, yet they did not beleeve they had any communion with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels, or that they were in ſo doing made partakers of the table of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels The Apoſtle anſwers that reply by a double argument; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The one taken from <hi>Iſrael after the fleſh,</hi> which did ſtill obſerve the cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the Law, and the legall ſacrifices; <hi>are not they which eat of the ſacrifices, partakers of the Altar?</hi> verſe. 18. and if of the Altar, then of the Idol which is over the Altar: and though the Idol be nothing, yet of the Divell to whom the Gentiles ſacrifice in the Idol, verſe 19. The other argument taken from the Chriſtians which are after the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:112137:16"/> ſpirit, which <hi>have an Altar too, Heb.</hi> 13. 10. though only myſticall, and far ſuperiour to theirs, becauſe more ſpirituall, of which they which are partakers, all worthy receivers have a communion with the things ſignified upon the Altar. The Corinthians themſelves were not ignorant of that; the Apoſtle ſpeaketh unto them as men that underſtood it was ſo, verſe 15. he carries it not out upon his own authority, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with their knowledge and aſſent: <hi>The cup of bleſſing which we bleſſe, is it not the Communion of the bloud of Chriſt? The bread which we breake, is it not the Communion of the body of Chriſt?</hi> and if there be communion in theſe, there is communion in thoſe; if with God and Chriſt in his Altars, then with the Idoll and the Devill in his Altars. This is the coherence, and the inference of the Text.</p>
            <p>This being already affirmed by the Apoſtle, and acknowledged by the Corinthians; for his interrogation, <hi>is it not?</hi> is <hi>Emphatica affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio:</hi> the whole argument is grounded upon an <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> which muſt not be denied; we ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e no more work to prove it, but waite upon the Holy Ghoſts further illuſtration of it, as he ſhall enable me, and your patience permit.</p>
            <p>There is one word for the moſt part praedominant in every Text, in this the word Communion is it; it is the chief veine in the body of it, and runs through every line and part, and it is very fit for the ſeaſon: Communion now eſpecially to be ſpoken of; when there is ſo much need of Communion, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> when faction and diviſion have made the thoughts of our hearts otherwiſe too great, there to have ſome thoughts of communion. That you may know what it is the better, you may conſider three Communions in the Text; they make each of <note n="3" place="margin">Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions.</note> them a ſeverall part.</p>
            <p>The firſt is Sacramentall, between the ſigns, and the things ſigned; <note n="1" place="margin">Calicis.</note> 
               <hi>The Cup of bleſſing which we bleſſe, is it not the Communion of the bloud of Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond is the Spirituall, between the things ſigned, and the <note n="2" place="margin">Capitis.</note> receivers; <hi>We are all partakers of one bread,</hi> which though laſt in the Text, is the ſecond to be inſerted; becauſe by the Apoſtle it is made the cauſe of</p>
            <p>The third Communion which is myſticall, between the receivers, <note n="3" place="margin">Corporis,</note> and themſelves one with another; <hi>for we that are many, are one bread, and one body;</hi> or to read the words more agreeable to the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, and therein I have the judgement of <hi>Beza; Becauſe there is but one bread, we that are many are one body.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:112137:16"/>
            <p>The firſt of theſe is peculiar to the ſeaſon, the Sacrament at the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity of the Sacrament; and the ground of the other two. For firſt there is <hi>Communio Calicis;</hi> and from thence ſprings the ſecond, our Communion with Chriſt, which is <hi>Capitis;</hi> and the third, our communion one with another, which is <hi>Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>poris:</hi> Saint <hi>Auſtine</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms them all. <hi>Sacramentum Pietatis, vinculum charitatis, ſignum u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatis, in Johan: Tract. 27.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I call them all Communions, becauſe they are all <hi>cum unione;</hi> and where there is union, there needs muſt be communion. Though <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the originall be ſayd only of the firſt which is Sacramentall; and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of the other, which is myſticall; yet they are made to dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer but as the effect and the cauſe; the ancient tranſlations know no difference between them, theſe laſt ought to have as full and as firm communion as the firſt: the end of that being to effect theſe, the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentall Communion for our ſpirituall, which is with Chriſt our head; and for our myſticall which is with one another, our body; <hi>Ideo inſtitutum ut corpus in terris capiti quod eſt in Coelis coadunetur. Aug. Ser. 28. in Erem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I begin with the firſt, <hi>Communio Calicis,</hi> the Sacramentall Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; and that becauſe it is the ſeale of all the reſt, the cement of all our <note n="2" place="margin">Calicis.</note> Communions, the Union of Communion. <hi>The Cup of bleſſing which we bleſſe, is it not the Communion of the Blood of Christ? The Bread which we break, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now a Communioni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s rightly defined a relation between two, or <note n="2" place="margin">Paci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> union of two or more in one thing which is common. In the ſacrament are two things; 1 The ſignes, 2 The things figned: Theſe two, by the <note n="1" place="margin"> Outward ſigne.</note> vertue of Divine operation, are made one, and thence is the Sacrament rightly ſtyled, A Communion: untill this Union come, there is no Communion at all, <hi>res terrena, &amp; Coelestis,</hi> which <hi>Iraeneus</hi> makes the parts of the Sacrament, never come together, they are at diſtance: look how high the heaven is from the earth, <hi>nec verit as ſigno, nec virtus Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento,</hi> ſaith <hi>Cyprian,</hi> till they meet in one conjunction; no truth there <note n="2" place="margin">I ward grac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> in the ſigne, no mercy here from the things ſigned, till mercy and truth both meet: all the vertue in the Sacrament is in the Union of the parts, and when that Union is, there is then a Communion.</p>
            <p>Take we a view of the parts; we muſt know them firſt, before we can ſay any thing of their Union, or of the Communion of them.</p>
            <p>The firſt is <hi>res terrena,</hi> the outward and viſible ſigne, which is in <note n="1" place="margin">Ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d fight.</note> effect but one, though in number two, even as the thing ſigned, one
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:112137:17"/> inviſible grace, or as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Bern:</hi> ſaith, rather <hi>unus Christus, in quo eſt om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis gratia:</hi> formally the ſignes and the things figned, are but one, but materially two, ſaith the School.</p>
            <p>They are two in number, ſo delivered by Chriſt at the firſt Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo exhibited by the Apoſtle, at the reinſtauration; and ſo recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by our Church, and all places where rightly received, at the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnization; and theſe two ſeverally conſidered, and not joyntly, the Bread aſunder from the Wine, the better to illuſtrate the death and paſſion of our Saviour, which was in the ſeparation of his Blood (which is the life) from the Body: but after they are received, they come together again, as they did this day, the Reſurrection, Chriſt now dying no more. The Commemoration is of Chriſts death, butthe Communion of Chriſt alive.</p>
            <p>The ſignes being two in number, are ſeverally to be repreſented, ſo in the Text, as they are at the time: we conſider them in that Order the Apoſtle layes them down, and content our ſelves with that reaſon which <hi>Hiereme</hi> and <hi>Anſelme</hi> give for his ſpeaking of the Cup firſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he had more to ſpeak of the bread laſt; not to invert the Order by a figure, but to divert his ſpeech whither he firſt intended it, Bread being a more proper Symboll of Union than Wine, not ſo ſoon fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling into parts, not ſo eaſie a ſubject of ſeparation as that is; and of Union his intent was to ſpeak.</p>
            <p>The Cup] that is firſt mentioned in the Text: by a Synecdoche, it is <note n="1" place="margin">The Cup.</note> put for the Wine in the Cup: That which is in the cup, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Chryſost.</hi> reades it: The Papiſts which boaſt ſo much of their keeping the lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſenſe of the Sacrament, allow of this figure, no man was ever ſo much eſt ranged from common ſpeech, as not to underſtand it: The Wine is the figne, the Cup by a figure put for it; but yet it is not the Wine in any cup. The Pſalmiſt ſpeaks of one, <hi>In the hand of the Lord there is a Cup, and the Wine is mixt, his enimies ſhall drink the dr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gs of it.</hi> And in <hi>Jeremy</hi> there <hi>is a cup of Wine of indignation, thoſe that did drink of it did ſpue and fall, and riſe no more.</hi> The Apoſtle diſting<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>es from that, and calls it, <hi>The Cup of bleſſing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Scripture uſeth commonly to expreſſe the bleſſing of God by the Metaphor of a cup: the abundance of bleſſing by the filling and overflowing of a cup, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 23. 5. The <hi>Navell</hi> of the Spouſe was <hi>as a round Cup, Can<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> 7. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. The Heathen uſed to crown their cups in the time of plenty; and <hi>Calvin</hi> reports that the Jews ſeats had their cup, an holy drinking, in which conſiſted the ſolemnity of their action, and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:112137:17"/> thence ſeems to come <hi>the Cup of Salvation</hi> the Pſalmiſt ſpeaks of, which they uſed to drink at their ſolemn meetings, in a gratulatory remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of their <hi>Deliverance;</hi> theſe are all farre inferiour unto that our Apoſtle ſpeaks of, which <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> he calls <hi>the Cup of bleſſing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Two wayes it may be called the Cup of bleſſing. Firſt, from Gods bleſſing for us. 2. From our bleſſing of God for it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Gods bleſſing of it for us; the words of Inſtitution are, <hi>He took the Cup and bleſſed it:</hi> in which there is a double power. 1. A power of Conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cration. 2. A power of Sanctification. By the firſt the Cup is made a Symboll, ſeparated from a civill or common uſe, to a religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious and holy intendment. By the ſecond, the Symboll is made effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall, to incorporate a right receiver into Chriſt, whereof it is made a Symbol. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> will extend to both, whichis the word for both. <hi>Oecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meni us</hi> takes it for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which is <hi>conſecrare. Beza</hi> for the other, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which is <hi>ſanctificare.</hi> Of the firſt there are infinite examples in the old Teſtament, bleſſing of the Sacrifices, the conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of them. Of the ſecond we have a pregnant one in thenew: <hi>every Creature of God is good, and is ſanctified by the Word of God,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 5. Both theſe make the Sacrament neceſſarily to beof Divine Inſtitution; none but God may appoint his figne, none bleſſeit but he, to make it effectuall to the receiver; other Creatures are of his bleſſing, in his firſt Inſtitution they had that, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. and by his bleſſing of them, we receive all our benefit from them; but that was but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, his bare word; and man lives by that, <hi>Every word which coneth from the mouth of God, Matth.</hi> 4. 4. But in his ſecond Inſtitution, there is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the good Word of God; much good muſt needs come from that; the Creature, the Cup which is bleſſed with it, is indeed <hi>the Cup of bleſſing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides the true effects of it in a worthy receiver, make it appear a Cup of bleſſing: it is the onely fap of our Spirituall life, the Autidote againſt the deepeſt Conſumption, the water of life, which whoſoever <hi>drinks worthily, ſhall never thirſt any m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re. Hauſtus ej us neihi Nectar erit,</hi> it is the Wine of Angels, the <hi>Cup of Salvation,</hi> the <hi>Waters of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort,</hi> the Spring-Head of eternall happines. In many things Chriſt hath deſerved well at our hands, but in none ſo much as this. <hi>Super omnia it reddit amabilem, bone Jeſu, Calix redemptionis meae,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bernard,</hi> it is a Cup of <hi>ſpiced Wine, Cant.</hi> 8. 2. Chriſt kept the good Wine till the laſt, and then gives it to his friends to drink: to his welbeloved to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ake her merry, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5. 1. it is a cup for the ſad heart to chear it, for
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:112137:18"/> the merry heart to confirm it; to quench our ſpirituall thirſt, to cure our ſpirituall grief: well may it receive from us theſe <hi>Eulogies,</hi> which receive by it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; ſo much bleſſing. There is <hi>Iſaacs</hi> bleſſing, The Dew of Heaven in it; and <hi>Calebs</hi> bleſſing, the ſprings above in it; and that which is above all, and worth all, there is Gods bleſſing, it is <hi>the Cup of bleſſing:</hi> from his bleſſing of it for us, that firſt, and that is <hi>poculum benedictum,</hi> as well as <hi>benedictionis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. From our bleſſing of God for it; <hi>The Cup of bleſſing which we bleſſe:</hi> there is the ſame word for it. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but yet not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the ſame ſence: <hi>Aliter nos Deum, aliter Dens nos:</hi> God bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth with power, and maketh that to be of force, which he ſaith, we bleſſe God withpraiſe; Gods bleſſing is reall, ours but verball: His <hi>cum effectu,</hi> ours at the beſt, but <hi>cum affectu:</hi> his is <hi>operativè, his word is ever a work with all, ours only <hi>optativè:</hi> it is the greater only that can bleſſe the leſſer, according to that of the Apoſtle, <hi>effectually:</hi> and he is the greateſt, we the leaſt; but <hi>ei benedicimus, cum de co bene dicimus;</hi> we bleſſe him, when we ſpeak well of him, when we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe his praiſe, when we ſpeak well of him: though ſo well as he hath deſerved of us, we cannot ſpeak. And hence is the Sacrament cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Euchariſtia,</hi> which is a giving of praiſe and thanks, which is the word of inſtitution, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26. 27. and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall are <hi>Synonima,</hi> ſaith <hi>Beza,</hi> to give praiſe and thinks, and to bleſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet this is not all the bleſſing is intended, <hi>Cui benedicimus:</hi> hath reference to the Cup, we bleſſe the Cup as well as God for the cup: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith <hi>Oecumenius.</hi> The conſecration of it is the bleſſing of it, the ſetting it a part to an holy uſe, the prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of God for it, the praying unto God for a bleſſing upon it; all theſe doth the word of bleſſing extend unto: and one thing more then theſe which is not to be forgot. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is a word for benevolence, and charity, The Sacrament it ſelf was wont by the Ancients to be called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a <hi>Collection, a Gathering;</hi> becauſe there uſed ever at ſuch gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the people to receive, to be a gathering for the poor withall. Let not this ſlip, call it a Cup of bleſſing from thence, let the poor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a bleſſing from you, that you may from God. <hi>Calix</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, of Gods benevolence and charity to you, of yours to his poor members for him; The firſt of theſe belongs only unto us, which have the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſteriall power of conſecration: <hi>We bleſſe,</hi> the Apoſtle ſpeaks it in our perſons: but the other belongs to you, as well as us, to bleſſe
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:112137:18"/> God for it, to pray for his bleſſing upon it, but then you muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that your bleſſing is not <hi>operativè,</hi> but only <hi>optativè,</hi> a wiſh; not a work; that belongs to God, as I ſaid before, but this to us: ſo the words <hi>cui benedicimus,</hi> may be ſaid of all: and that is all needs be ſaid of it: The firſt ſigne, the Cup of bleſſing.</p>
            <p>I paſſe to the ſecond: the Bread which we break; Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe ſignes are <note place="margin">The b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ead.</note> one, as <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſaid of <hi>Pharoabs</hi> dreams; one in nature, yet two in num<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber, they make both but one part of the Sacrament: one thing is in effect ſignified by both; yet one was not thought ſufficient for usby our Saviour, either to ſhew his death, which is the end of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: or to ſeal to our faith, which is the uſe of it, and by two ſignes, as by twowitneſſes will be an end of ſtrife.</p>
            <p>We may yeeld three reaſons for it, why theſe, and why both theſe are exhibited by our Saviour.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, in both theſe conſiſts the chief maintenance of our life, they are the principall ſupporters of it; Bread alone will not ſerve, <hi>Man li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth not by bread only;</hi> nor yet wine alone, there is no living alone by the Cup, though ſome make a ſhift to ſtay by it long enough, yet they cannot live by it; man is made of fleſh and bloud, and needs both to feed him, Bread and Wine; and in our ſpirituall food, Chriſt would have no want: he takes them both, they are the beſt, the clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt food of our life, and ſo fitteſt to repreſent the food of the ſoul.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, There are no ſuch things to ſhew the death of Chriſt by, as theſe: mark how the Bread is thraſhed, and ground, and ſifted, and baked before it can be fit good; And the wine, ſtript and trod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſed, <hi>preſſum antequam expreſſum,</hi> before it is made fit to drink: So was Chriſts body, The Plowers plowed upon his back, the ſouldiers thraſhed him, the Jews fifted him, the teeth of the Lyons to <hi>Ignatius,</hi> the teeth of death to him, ground him ſmall enough, the grave was the Oven to bake him; So was his bloud; the Croſſe was the preſſe: The Prophet might well ask him, why are his <hi>Garments red?</hi> So many thorns, and nails, ſuch a wound in his ſide, were win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows enough to let out all his bloud: The Bread and the Wine, very aptly intimate all this; and this is even all, the end of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, The naturall body of Chriſt, is not only ſignified by the Sacrament, but alſo his myſticall, which is his Church, which is one made up of many beleevers, and is not the Bread one, made of many grains? and the Cup one, made of many grapes? no ſuch Symbolls
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:112137:19"/> of Vnion as theſe are. So are the faithfull kneaded, and knit together, ſo incorporated into one: and therefore ſaith Saint <hi>Auſtine,</hi> Chriſt commends unto us his body and bloud in thoſe things, <hi>quae ex multis redigunt in unum,</hi> that ſo the Sacrament might be <hi>ſignum unitatis,</hi> a very Communion, as it ſhall appear after: and to be this is another end of the Sacrament.</p>
            <p>The ſignes then are both fit, other reaſons might be given, but theſe are the chief: but yet a reaſon would be given, why the Apoſtle calls not this ſigne, the Bread of bleſſing, as well as he did the other, <hi>the Cup of bleſſing;</hi> it is to be obſerved beſides, that in the 11 to the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians,</hi> Verſe 24. where the Apoſtle fals upon this matter again, there he mentions bleſſing only of the Bread, and not of the Cup at all; belike he thought once naming it in both, was enough for both, and that his ſaying of it once was enough to ſend us to his, <hi>quod accepi à D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mina,</hi> to the firſt inſtitution of it, and there we finde them both bleſſed a like, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26. 26, 27. and it is worth the marking: that the word which the Apoſtle uſeth for the bleſſing of the Cup, is the ſame that the Evangeliſt uſeth there for the bleſſing of the Bread; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in both; and the word which the Apoſtle uſeth in the other for the bleſſing of the Bread, is the ſame that the Evangeliſt uſeth for the bleſſing of the Cup: it is <hi>Euchariſtia</hi> in both, to ſhew that the words are both of one ſence, and that the ſignes were both alike bleſſed.</p>
            <p>But beſides, he ſpeaks not here of the bleſſing of the Bread, becauſe he was to mention a neceſſary Ceremony, belonging to the ſigne, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing indeed a part of it, which may not be left out; and that is, the breaking of the Bread, and that alone made the words of the Text full: <hi>The Bread which we break;</hi> and of this minde is <hi>Pareus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Breaking of the Bread is a moſt ſignificant Ceremony annexed to the ſigne, it doth beſt ſhew the Lords death of any: not that any ſuch thing was done to Chriſts body, a <hi>bone of him could not be broken:</hi> I will not ſay with Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> he ſuffereth that to be done in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, which he could not ſuffer to be done him upon the Croſſe, we may not think that he doth ſuffer any thing there, neither doth that Father think ſo: but it is broken to ſhew his many ſufferings, of what nature, of what number ſoever they were, breaking is a <hi>Metaphor</hi> to expreſſe them, and the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> hath it of his paſſion; <hi>He was broken for our iniquities, Iſai 53.</hi> and the Apoſtle ſpeaks it fully, <hi>Hoc eſt Corpus meum quod pro vobis frangitur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Ceremony our Saviour himſelf uſed at the inſtitution, <hi>He</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:112137:19"/> 
               <hi>brake the Bread:</hi> to ſhew indeed that he was not only broken in his paſſion, but he was willingly broken, that he did break himſelf; for indeed, the nails, and the thorns, and the ſpear could not have broken him, not ſo much as his skin, no more then the ſouldiers could break his legs, had not he been willing to have it done, to be broken; had not he been principall agent in it, as well as ſole Patient of it, and broke himſelf.</p>
            <p>As he uſed it then, from his inſtitution, we uſe it ſtill. <hi>The Bread which we break:</hi> and indeed, the rather to ſhew that we our ſelves were chief act ours in his breaking, it was for us, for our ſakes he was content to be broken, we did ſit, our ſins, all of us had an hand in breaking him: and in ſign of that it is ſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l, <hi>The Bread which we break.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the chief cauſe of our breaking of it, is that which Saint <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome</hi> gives <hi>patitur frangi ut omnes impleat;</hi> every one could not take a little; if Chriſt did not ſuffer himſelf to be made ſo little; and to ſhew he gave his body to be crucified for all, he appoints his ſigne to be broken for all. This Ceremony and no other, he appointed for this ſigne, we may not ſo well away with that of the Papiſts, which uſe round Wafers, and give to every one, one, no breaking at all; nor yet, ſo properly allow of that of ours in ſome places, cutting and mangling of the Bread, and not any ſigne of breaking; Chriſt was known at firſt in the miracle of five Loaves, and there was breaking of Bread, after the Reſurrection he was made known unto the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples by <hi>breaking of bread:</hi> The Apoſtles practice in the Primitive Church was, <hi>breaking of Bread,</hi> and in the Sacrament he makes it his Ceremony, <hi>He brake the bread:</hi> all Authority, all Antiquity makes eſpecially for this Ceremony, and being it ſelf of ſuch uſe, it behoves us to make much of it too: and ſo much to be ſpoken of it, and of the firſt part of the Sacrament, <hi>The outward ſigne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We be come now to the ſecond part of the Sacrament, <hi>Res caelestis,</hi> 
               <note n="1" place="margin">part. The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Grace.</note> 
               <hi>The inward and ſpirituall grace:</hi> which anſwers to the ſignes in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; yet is in nature but one; <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nus Chriſtus in quo omnis gratia,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bernard,</hi> yet Chriſt gave both: <hi>His body to be crucified, and his bloud to be ſhed:</hi> his body to be meat indeed, his bloud to be drink indeed: and in the Sacrament he inſtituted ſignes of both: <hi>The Cup which we bleſſe, the Bread which we break:</hi> they are both as yet to be conſidered ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, till we come to the Communion; to their coming into one, the joyning of them both together. As yet we take the Text in parts;
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:112137:20"/> the ſecond part is now to be taken notice of, and in that, according to the order of the Apoſtle.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The Bloud of Chriſt] Some take it <hi>Metaphorically</hi> for the ſoul <note n="1" place="margin">The bloud.</note> of Chriſt, ſo in the Law: <hi>Sanguis eſt anima.</hi> Chriſt indeed gave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and he did conſiſt of ſoul and body both, he had not took upon hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our nature elſe, if he had not had a perfect humane ſoul, neither had he redeemed any ſoul at all, if he had not had a ſoul himſelf: <hi>Tolle animam Chriſti &amp; Praeſta quid Deus redemit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Tertullian</hi> to <hi>Marcion.</hi> And in his ſoul he ſuffered more then in his body; the fears, the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows, the wounds of it, are paſt any mans expreſſion; witneſſe his heavy complaining, <hi>Anima mea tristis eſt:</hi> his ſtrong crying: <hi>Pater ſi poſſibile eſt:</hi> his bloudy ſweating, his fear, his whole Agony, none but he could ever feel ſuch wounds, the guilt of a world of ſin, the ſence of the wrath of God, none but his ſoul could carry ſuch ſorrows: Something it is meet ſhould be to remember them, as well as thoſe of his body: the ſoul cannot be reſembled by any thing: the bloud car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries the neereſt reſemblance. <hi>Sanguis eſt anima,</hi> or at leaſt, <hi>in loco ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae,</hi> we may allow of that.</p>
            <p>If not that, then take it literally: his naturall bloud, the very ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of it, that which he gave ſo liberally to be ſhed upon the Croſſe: the Bloud of the Paſchall Lamb, the bloud of all the Jewiſh ſacrifices, were but <hi>Commonſtratives</hi> of that: that is not now to be had, not to be ſhown again. Chriſt ſuffered once for all: his offering of himſelf was but once ſubſtantially to be made, and made by himſelf; his fleſh, and bloud are now glorified with his Godhead, and become impatible, <hi>Care &amp; ſanguis uſurpàrunt regnum Dei in Chriſto,</hi> ſaith <hi>Tertullian,</hi> only we remember that: and the Wine in the Cup is the neareſt reſemblance of it; not <hi>Commonſtrative</hi> as the Type, but <hi>Commemorative,</hi> of the Truth; of his Bloud. That</p>
            <p>We may adde to it: the Bloud of Chriſt <hi>Metonimically,</hi> the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of his Bloud; that which he effected by ſhedding of his Bloud, the remiſſion of ſins, our reconcilement, and peace with God, our <hi>Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe. Sanctification, Redemption, 1 Cor.</hi> 1. 30. All theſe through his Bloud, through Faith in his Bloud. His Bloud which ſpeaketh better things then the Bloud of <hi>Abel:</hi> this cryed for vengeance, his was <hi>Sanguis clamans</hi> too, but it ſpake, <hi>Father forgive them:</hi> it cryed for mercy and reconcilement. The benefit is ſpecially intended by the Bloud, the purging of ſin, and purchaſing of peace: this is chiefly to be remembred, and we do this when we ſay the Bloud of Chriſt.
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:112137:20"/> For it is not the ſubſtance of his Bloud, that cleanſeth, it comes not to all, it comes not at all: but the merit of it by the efficacy and vertue of it; this was the end of our ſhewing it, and this is the ſumme of what may be ſaid of the firſt: The Bloud of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The next is the Body of Chriſt, we conſider that alſo two wayes, <note n="2" place="margin">The Body.</note> and both of them are <hi>intenſive</hi> in my Text: Firſt, <hi>Subſtantiam Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris:</hi> Secondly, <hi>Efficaciam &amp; meritum,</hi> both are to be remembred in this part.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The Body the ſubſtance of it, <hi>The ſame Body which was cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified: Corpus quod pro vobis traditum eſt,</hi> are the words of the inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution. The <hi>Syrian</hi> interpreter renders it, <hi>Pagra,</hi> which ſaith <hi>Beza</hi> is properly, <hi>Corpus mortuum,</hi> it is to ſhew his death, and it cannot be ſhewed plainer then by ſuch a word, which ſignifies his dead Body; That we muſt ſhew: the Bread which is broken is his ſigne, <hi>Corporis quod frangitur, which is broken for you, 1 Cor. 11. 24.</hi> And when we ſhew that, we ſhew his w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>unds, and ſtripes, his beating, and bruſing, and bearing, all that he did ſuffer on his body; the Commemoration is to be of his paſſion.</p>
            <p>Secondly, we remember the merit of his paſſion; that, for which he gave his Body to be crucified; the purchaſe for which he paid ſuch a price: the remiſſion of ſins: they were all laid upon his Body: <hi>Davids</hi> ſin upon <hi>Davids</hi> ſon; <hi>Dominus tranſtulit peccata tua,</hi> are the words of <hi>Nathan</hi> to him; not <hi>abſtulit,</hi> but <hi>tranſtulit,</hi> from thee upon him; and not only his, but ours, he bare our ſins, faith <hi>Iſaiah 53. He bare them on his Body on the Tree, 1 Pet. 2. 24.</hi> we were ſold to ſin, to death; our body to the grave, our ſoul to hell. To corruption to torment he gave himſelf for us, both body and ſoul, <hi>ut redimeret,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Paul, Tit.</hi> 2. 14. Remiſſion, Redemption, are the main ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of his paſſion; we cannot remember his death, but we muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the deſert, and merit of it. So I have done with the parts ſeverally, the outward ſigne, the inward grace: <hi>Rem terrenam &amp; C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtem:</hi> we come now to the Communion, or their coming into one, to make up the Sacrament: though the one part be on earth, the other in heaven; and look how high the heaven is from the earth, yet they may meet, they muſt meet, elſe there will be no Sacrament at all: <hi>Nulla virtus Sacramento,</hi> ſaith <hi>Cyprian;</hi> they muſt be in <hi>Common,</hi> or there will be no <hi>Communion:</hi> and then the Text will not be true, which ſaith; <hi>The Cup of bleſſing, which we bleſſe, is it not the Communion of the Bloud of Chriſt? The Bread which we break, is it not the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n of the Body of Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:112137:21"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Communion</hi> is ever, <hi>cum unione;</hi> when two or more meet in one, <note n="2" place="margin"> The Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en.</note> there is a Communion. It is divers wayes: either by nature, which is <hi>Phyſicall;</hi> as when ſoul and body are united into one perſon, there is Communion between them, by reaſon of tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> union. Secondly, by miracle, which is <hi>Metaphyſicall;</hi> as when two Natures, God and man were united into one Chriſt. There is alſo Communion between them by virtue of that Union: neither of theſe is this heer; for it is no ſubſtantiall, no <hi>Hypoſtaticall <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion,</hi> and yet the Fathers have uſed both theſe to illuſtrate this Commun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on. Thirdly, by <hi>locall coberence;</hi> as when many ſtones are in one heap. Fourthly, by <hi>actuall inexiſtence;</hi> as where accidences, as colours, &amp;c. are in one ubject, none of theſe yet: for the body and bloud of Chriſt may not be thought to be, Locally, Actually, any where but in Heaven: The Heavens muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain him till his ſecond, and laſt coming. There is yet another way. Fiftly, <hi>Intellectually, Sacramentally,</hi> which conſiſts in meer relation, which is the nature of Communion.</p>
            <p>Sacramentall Union is that Communion we ſpeak off: and it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in a Myſticall, and Mutuall relation, between the ſignes, and the things ſigned: <hi>Sacramentum eſt rei Sacrae ſignum,</hi> is Saint <hi>Auſtins</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition, and allowed, and approved by all, when the ſigne comes to ſignifie the ſacred thing, it comes to be a Sacrament; and this coming is the Communion. We look to two things: 1. The cauſe of it. 2. The effects.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Divine inſtitution is the cauſe. The Rain-bow (it is generally <note n="1" place="margin">The cauſe.</note> agreed upon, was before the floud, yet) was not any ſigne of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of God, of not deſtroying the world with a deluge, till after the floud; it was in <hi>nube</hi> to be ſeen there, but not <hi>ſignum</hi> in <hi>nube,</hi> till God firſt appointed it his ſigne to <hi>No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h.</hi> The Wine in the Cup, the Bread on the Table were in uſe before, bleſſed in their creation for temporall food; but not in any uſe to a ſpirituall life, till bleſſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain at their inſtitution; they were not ſignes of any ſacred things, till God appointed them his ſignes to his Apoſtles; and as words which come to the ears, are <hi>ſigna rerum,</hi> of thoſe things which the minde means to expreſſe: if aptly appointed, and do conveigh the very things to the underſtanding of the Auditor: if he be quick, you would wonder at it, to ſee how ſoon, at a word ſpeaking, a thing of never ſo great diſtance can come to his knowledge: ſo theſe earthly things, which are <hi>ſigna rei ſacrae,</hi> which come unto the eyes, and the other ſenſes, being aptly appointed by the firſt inſtitutor, do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veigh
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:112137:21"/> unto the faith of the worthy receiver, the very things themſelves; and though they were before at never ſo much diſtance, they come to be preſent to our faith, as other things expreſſed by words, are to our reaſon and ſence. To make ſignes of ſuch, belongs only unto him which can give the things: and his body and bloud none can give but himſelf; none can make a ſigne to be a means to conveigh it, to be apledge to confirm it, but he: the Elements are empty and <hi>non ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificant; Accedat verbum ad Elementum,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auſtin:</hi> his word<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> his work that comes, and it becomes a Sacrament; the ſigne is made effectually, to ſignifie the ſacred thing: and that making a ſigne, is the cauſe of the Relation of the Communion firſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, being ſo made by the virtue of the Divine Inſtitution, <note n="2" place="margin">The effects.</note> the effects of Sacramentall Communion follow. The ſignes them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, have a Communication of the Proprieties of the things ſignes: <hi>Communicatio Idiomatum</hi> is the chief effect: As by the Hypoſtaticall Union of the two natures in Chriſt, the humane nature is inveſted into the Divine, the manhood being aſſumed, is allowed to carry a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the properties of the Godhead, in the perſon of Chriſt. And thence comes it, that <hi>the Son of God</hi> is called, <hi>the Son of man: and the Lord of life was crucified and ſlain. The Mother of God, the Bloud of God,</hi> are uſuall ſpeeches with the Fathers: ſo in this Sacramentall Union by virtue of that Communion, in the words of inſtitution, the Bread is called the Body of Chriſt, the Wine his Bloud. When we give the Bread we ſay: <hi>The Body of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, &amp;c.</hi> the Cup, we ſay, <hi>The Bloud of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> The Bread, though it be <hi>res terrena,</hi> is called <hi>Panis vitae,</hi> the food of Angles, the Bread which came down from Heaven, The food of the ſoul: <hi>Panem Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> S <hi>Cyprian</hi> calls it, and not only <hi>Panem Domini:</hi> and all this <hi>per Metonymiam ſigni,</hi> becauſe of the Communion it hath with the things ſigned, with the Body of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Neither is this Communion only <hi>nominall,</hi> but alſo <hi>reall:</hi> the very ſubſtance of Chriſts Body and Bloud is by it communicated to worthy receivers: they are verily, and indeed, taken and received of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, ſaith our Church. Not in the ſignes eſſentially, but by the ſignes effectually; for we muſt hold us to this, that the Union is not Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, nor Metaphyſicall, not Eſſentiall, nor Locall, but Intellectuall, and Sacramentall, and yet reall, and not only nominall. Ask what the Bread, and Wine is, I anſwer the Body and Bloud of Chriſt. Ask me how or which way: I anſwer Sacramentally; becauſe they
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:112137:22"/> are the Communion of the Body and Bloud of Chriſt, and not that properly neither; for a ſubſtance cannot be a Relation, but by a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonymy of the effect; becauſe they make us partakers of the Body and Bloud of Chriſt, they are called the Communion of his Body and Bloud.</p>
            <p>And being <hi>Communis ſubſtantiae,</hi> they are alſo <hi>Communio efficaciae,</hi> they make us partakers of the merit of Chriſts Body and Bloud; thoſe things ever bring their worth and dignity with them, remiſſion of ſins, redemption, ſanctification, ſalvation; all graces come along with Chriſt, <hi>in quo eſt omnis gratia. Habent omnia qui habent deum ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bentem omnia.</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>August.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as there is Communion with them, ſo there is communition from them: we may not amiſſe take the word <hi>Communio, a Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endo:</hi> that is to be reckoned among the benefits we receive; ſo our Church reckons it, the ſtrengthening of our ſouls: <hi>Vis ſemper fortior in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nione;</hi> nothing can prevail; againſt earth, when heaven is joyned to it: if God be with us who can be againſt us? and he is with us heer by Sacramentall Union he comes into the Communion.</p>
            <p>Thus have we made the ſignes, and the things ſigned to meet, and but to meer, for we may go no further; my Text calls it but a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, and I take it to be a full expoſition of our Saviours words at the Inſtitution; <hi>This</hi> (ſpeaking of the Bread) <hi>is my Body,</hi> ſaith he, A Communion of his Body, ſaith the Text: <hi>This</hi> (the Wine) <hi>is my Bloud:</hi> A Communion of his Bloud, ſaith the Apoſtle. If a Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of it, then not it, as the Papiſts will have it; Sacramentally we allow it to be it, <hi>ſignum rei;</hi> not it ſubſtantially, but onely a Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of it. Had it been it, groſſely, carnally, The Apoſtle ſhould have ſaid, not the Cup, but the Bloud, not the Bread, but the Body; For the Bread, and the Wine both according to their Doctrines are gone, only accidences remains, then he had committed no ſmall <hi>Tau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tology.</hi> The Bread which is my Body, is the Communion of the Body of Chriſt: The Wine in the Cup, which is the Bloud it ſelf, is a Communion, of the Bloud of Chriſt; Indeed they do not well away with the Communion, it croſſeth them too much, therefore they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt croſſe it out. It may appear by other particula<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s. Their private Maſſe ſhuts it out quite: Their publique Maſſe juſtles it out not a little: They have no Communion of the Cup at all; The Laity are not allowed it: and if there be no Cup, there is no Communion there: neither is there any <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> if not it; (I do only obſerve
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:112137:22"/> that by the way) for the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, from whence comes the name of <hi>Eucharist,</hi> is no where uſed at the Inſtitution, but at the Cup, and if no Cup, no giving of thanks for it, of the Peoples part none, which have part of none: So Communion and Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt they ſhuffle out; and worſe then this, <hi>Chriſtum denuo crucifigunt,</hi> while they ſeparate his Bloud from his Body, without any Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, without any coming together again. But this is no place for controverſies: be we ſure to keep it right, as we do call it right: and from this very Text we call it a Communion.</p>
            <p>And that we may keep it right, there muſt be on our parts a coming on to the Communion: where the dead body is, there the Eagles will be gathered together: and no where is the dead Body of our Saviour more plainly repreſented: G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t we up upon the Wing of pure Devotion, of holy Meditation, ſore we aloft like Eagles: <hi>Surſum Corda:</hi> if we come not, there may be Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion for others, none for us: for only thoſe that receive, are of the Communion, thoſe that cate of the things of the Altar, are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the Altar; if yee cat not, you are not of the Communion of the Body of Chriſt; If you drink not you are not of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the Bloud.</p>
            <p>But yet, look how you come, for if you come unworthily, you will not be of that Communion neither: we may not ſo tye the things ſigned to the ſignes, the Body and Bloud, to the Bread and Wine, as if whoſoever receives the one muſt alſo receive the other. Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> reſolves it well: <hi>Tantum utilitatis quiſque reportat quantum Vaſculo fidei Colligit;</hi> others which come without faith, <hi>Lambunt Petram, ſed nec inde mel ſugunt, nec oleum:</hi> They go away without joy; becauſe they came without faith: Like <hi>Mary Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalen,</hi> they ſee the Lord Corporall, the clean Linnen lye, wherein our Saviour was wrapped, but finde him not, and ſay without any comfort; <hi>They have taken away the Lord. Panem Domini</hi> they finde, but not <hi>Panem Dominum;</hi> neither do I know how they ſhould; he is preſent only to the eye of faith, not of ſence: <hi>Non ventris ſed men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis cibus eſt;</hi> The hand, the mouth, the teeth, the ſtomack of Faith: <hi>Credere eſt edere.</hi> Come with this then, and we come right, we ſhall no doubt be of the Communion.</p>
            <p>And as you come with Faith, ſo you muſt come with Love: gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and forgiving, are the tenour of it: both are done to you heer by Chriſt, he gives you his Body and Bloud, and they are given for
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:112137:23"/> the remiſſion of ſins: both muſt be done by you, unto your bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren. Then there will be a full Communion on all ſides: of Chriſt with us by mercy and trueth, of us with Chriſt by Faith and Love? of the outward ſignes, and the inward graces, of both with the worthy receivers: of the receivers with themſelves; for ſo from this Sacramentall Communion, will ſpring our ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall with Chriſt our head; and from thence our Myſticall, with h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s Body the Members, till at laſt we come to a perfect Union with the Communion of the Saints, which are compleate in Heaven, which with our Saviour ſtill drink of the fruit of this Vine, new in the Kingdom: Whither he bring us all for his Infinit merits, and mercies, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="sermon">
            <head>THE FOURTH SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>1 COR. 10. 17.</bibl>
               <q>For we that are many, are one Bread and one Body: becauſe we are all partakers of one Bread.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>WE be come now to the ſecond part of the Text; the ſecond Communion, that which is ſpirituall, between the things, and the receivers; <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nus Chriſtus in quo eſt omnis gratia,</hi> he is the thing ſigned between him and us, and it is properly called <hi>Communio</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio. Capitis.</note> 
               <hi>Capitis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Communio Calicis</hi> was well premiſed, becauſe it is the ground and foundation of the other Communions; for thence iſſues this our Communion with Chriſt, <hi>They that eat of the Sacrifices are partakers of the Altar,</hi> Verſe 18. By eating we enter into it, and upon that we pitch it, in the laſt words of the Text, <hi>We that are many, are one Bread, becauſe we are all partakers of one Bread.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alimentum fit Alitum,</hi> ſaith the Phyloſopher; ſo it is in our ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall food: <hi>Except we eat the Body of Christ, he dwelleth not in us;</hi> but
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:112137:23"/> if we eat him, if we digeſt him, both which are to be done by faith, as hath been ſhewed before, <hi>Participatione ea</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">Reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctu Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis Idloma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum.</note> 
               <hi>corporaliter nobis inerit Chriſtus,</hi> ſaith <hi>Cyrill;</hi> his very fleſh is made ours, as we are in him by a certain <hi>Phyſicall Identity</hi> in the <hi>Hypoſtaticall <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> our humane nature and his Divine made one: ſo he ſhall be in us though neither by tranſubſtantiation, nor by conſubſtantiation, not by naturall, nor corporall contract; but by ſpirituall and reall U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, his perſon, and ours made one. <hi>Sacramentally</hi> he is in his ſigne; <hi>Spiritually</hi> in the receiver.</p>
            <p>The receivers are all thoſe, which do worthily partake of one Bread; their Union with Chriſt, was the end of that I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtitution of Chriſt: that Sacramentall Communion was to be a mean to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffect, and a ſeal to confirme our ſpirituall: <hi>ideo inſtitutum ut Corpus in terris capiti quod est in Coelis coadunetur,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Auſten: Panis Daminus</hi> to the right receiver comes along, <hi>cum pane Domini.</hi> They that eate of the Sacrifices, are partakers of the Altar, is a Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion unqueſtionably true; and then by conſequence, if they partake of one Bread, they alſo partake of one Body, and of this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſaith my Text. <hi>We are all partakers of one Bread.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And it needs not trouble us, that the word in the Originall is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, when before it was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; there Communion, but partak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re; as if the Communion between the ſignes, and the things ſigned, were fuller, then it is between the receivers and them. Take one as the eff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ct, and the other as the cauſe, ſo <hi>Beza</hi> will have it, becauſe by the partaking of the Bread, we come into the ſociety, and Communion of Chriſt: So the Apoſtle ſeems to intend it, we are one body, one with him, becauſe we are all partakers of one Bread; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſymbolorum,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is <hi>rerum,</hi> we place not our U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with Chriſt in participation, but in the effect of that which is Communion, we fetch it thence, not ſeat it there; and as from Chriſts participation with our nature, where the Apoſtle uſeth the ſame word, becauſe the Children were partakers of fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſh and bloud, he alſo likewiſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> took part, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. 14. did reſult the Hypoſtaticall Union of our nature with him: So from our participation of one Bread, the Symboll of the Sacrament, of which <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> doth reſult the ſpirituall <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Union of his perſon with us. Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> upon my Text ſaith it; <hi>non par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipatione taniùn &amp; acceptatione, ſed <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitate Communicamus: Quem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>admodum enim corpus unicum eſt Chriſto; ita &amp; nos per hunc panem</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:112137:24"/> 
               <hi>unione conjungimur.</hi> So that, though not in that, the act of partaking of that one Bread; yet by that, we come to the Communion of Chriſt, though the Bread be but the Symboll of this Society, yet upon the partaking of that, we come into the Communion of the thing it ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lf, which is ſigned by it, ſo that there is full out as firm Communion hence, as was before;</p>
            <p>And being a Communion between Chriſt and us, we call it rightly <hi>Communio Capitis,</hi> in the Allegory of a Body, (which the Apoſtle he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r alludes unto) Chriſt will not away with any other place then the head in the Body Myſticall, the ſupream Head: In all other Allegories as of the Vine, and the branches, he will be <hi>the R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot</hi> which bears all, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. 18, and <hi>Radix arboris Caput eſt;</hi> of the family, he the Maſter; and <hi>Dominus</hi> is ever <hi>Capu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> domus:</hi> In the Building <hi>caput Anguli;</hi> in the Book, <hi>in Capite libri;</hi> and our tenour if it be right, muſt hold in <hi>Capite</hi> too. All the Communion we have with him, depends upon this Relation, and it is enough, we need deſire no more. <hi>Communio Capitis,</hi> is neer enough.</p>
            <p>This Communion of the Head with the Body, is neither Phyſicall nor Corporall, but Spirituall: the naturall man cannot perceive it: how the Head in Heaven may be united to a Body in Earth, is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a riddle to humane reaſon. Who ſhall fetch down Chriſt from above, or if he muſt be above ſtill, <hi>Quomodo teneb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentem,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Auſten,</hi> in the perſon of a naturall man? This is chiefly to be explained, and about it two things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. What this Union is. <note n="2" place="margin">Parts.</note>
               </item>
               <item>2. Wherein it doth appear.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Eſſe,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Cognoſci,</hi> are the materiall points about it.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. It is Spirituall: the eye of Faith, and not of Sence can diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern <note n="1" place="margin"> Eſſe.</note> it, <hi>Mitte manum fidei, &amp; tractaſti,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auſten</hi> in anſwer to <hi>Quomodo tenebo abſentem.</hi> That there is a Union, a being one with Chriſt, is plain from that prayer of our Saviour for his Diſciples, and not for them only, but for all beleevers: <hi>Father I pray thee that they may be one in us, as thou art one in me, and I in thee, John</hi> 17. 21. but that being one is <hi>tanti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m ſpiritu &amp; fide,</hi> ſaith <hi>Maldonate;</hi> and that <hi>ſicut,</hi> there is not <hi>aequalitis,</hi> but <hi>cujuſdam ſimilitudinis,</hi> ſaith <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome;</hi> for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſentiall Union, which is eternall, between the Father and the Son; or Hypoſtaticall Union, which is ſubſtantiall between the Sonne and our nature, it cannot be; our perſonall Union is ſpirituall, and no more.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:112137:24"/>
            <p>Spirituall, becauſe it is wrought by the Spirit; Faith is the fruit of Spirit, and it is that which is the very eſſence of this Union, the neereſt ſymbolically quality that can be, between Chriſt and us. In every Union of naturall things, <hi>vis unitiva,</hi> ſome quality or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there muſt be, by which they agree in one, ſomething <hi>Medie Naturae.</hi> Fire and water can never be reconciled alone, becauſe they have none: in that greateſt union of all, of God and Man, Chriſt himſelf was <hi>factus Mediae Naturae.</hi> a Mediator: Earth and Heaven had never met, but by his being exalted in <hi>Medium locum,</hi> the Croſſe was between both, and Heaven there was content to ſtoop loweſt, Earth being able to riſe no higher. In this Union of our perſons with Chriſt, <hi>cum Capite,</hi> Faith is that, <hi>vis unitiva,</hi> the Cement by which <hi>Caput Anguli</hi> is joyned to the building, and yet that is but a conjunction; no thing is conveyed into the other parts from it: it is therefore more, the Ligament and ſinew by which the Head is united to the Body, and thorow which is conveyed all the benefit of being, and motion to the members. <hi>Similitudo imaginis,</hi> that likeneſſe, after which man was created, had united him to God; but that was ſo defaced by the fall, God knew him not for his Creature; nothing like in the world was left, all ſimilitude between God and him loſt, till Chriſt repayred that Image again, waſht it with his Bloud, and ſet Faith in the face of it; by that they may meet, there is ſomething like to bring them into liking, to make an union.</p>
            <p>Neither is this Imaginary, a device for ſpeculation; but reall ſpirituall things have the beſt and trueſt reality in them: The Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Illuſtrate it divers wayes: as fire is united to red hot Iron, actually and virtually both, it is no where more viſible, more powerfull for the time; as the Beams of the Son are united to the ayre; as Wine and water contemperated and mixt together; as wax to wax, and made into one lump: The Apoſtle giveth a plain inſtance, he that is coupled with an Harlot is one body; <hi>Erunt duo in carne una,</hi> is the couſummation of marriage: in that ſence it is called a Myſtery, between Chriſt and his Church: So he that is joyned unto Chriſt, is one Spirit.</p>
            <p>One Spirit, is but <hi>Metalepſis:</hi> one ſpirituall body is the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>Faith</hi> on our parts, the <hi>Spirit</hi> on his part concurre, and make a union.</p>
            <p>You may ſee more, the ground of this will confirme the truth
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:112137:25"/> of it, and it is in the words of the Text. <hi>We are all partakers of one Bread.</hi> There are foure ſorts of unions, both Scriptures and Fathers uſe to Illuſtrate. Firſt, Eternall, between the Father and the Sonne. Secondly, Hypoſtaticall, between the divine nature and humane. Thirdly, Conjugall and Matrimo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iall, between husband and wife. Fourthly, Allegoricall, as between the Vine and branch, between Head and Members, between Bread and the receivers: each would afford matter for a Sermon, I muſt inſiſt only on that laſt.</p>
            <p>That which we eate turns in <hi>carnem &amp; ſanguinem; alimentum fit alitum,</hi> if ſo be, it be digeſted firſt, elſe it doth not: <hi>Cibus Iadi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtus famem ſatiat animalem, non naturalem.</hi> It comes not into union with the body, by which it might grow ſtronger, but is forceably caſt out, though it ſtay the ſtomack for a time: So it is in our ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall food; they which know not how to digeſt it by faith, have their appetite ſtaid, not their groweth, and ſtrength augmented; but if it be digeſted, it comes into one, it becomes one with us.</p>
            <p>Thus are Chriſt and we made one: We have the Symboll, the Sacrament, the Seal of it, of which we all eate, and wherefore do we eate, but <hi>ut uniamur?</hi> What is more ours then that we have eaten? A neerer <hi>Symboll</hi> could not poſſibly be thought on, of our incorporation, and making one with him; and yet S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith more; <hi>Et manducat nos &amp; m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mducatur à nobis quo arctiùs illi aſtringa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur.</hi> In one and the ſame action he feeds on us, we feed on him: his joy fills us; our faith feeds him: his body, his bloud, his ſuff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, his righteouſneſſe are meat and drink to us; our faith, our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, our obedience, our ſalvation, are meat and drink to him: and thoſe are one, (though the compariſon be without compa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, yet) our Saviour himſelf prayes it may be ſo; <hi>John 17. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Bernard</hi> proves it is ſo, between Chriſt and us: we one with him abiding by faith and love; he one with us, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iding by peace and truth: yet not in that manner one, as they are; the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nce of our nature and ſubſtance ſtill remains, which are one in the Father and the Sonne: only the diverſity of our <note n="a" place="margin">Non c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hrren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narum, ſed co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentia volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m Lern.</note> wills reconciled, makes us one, one with the Father and the Sonne, and ſo one, <hi>ut Deus &amp; homo unus ſpiritus certa &amp; abſoluta veritate dicantur, ſi ſibi glutino amori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> inb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reant.</hi> So ſure are we one, ſo reall is our ſpirituall Union with Chriſt our Head; if we eat the Bread, if we digeſt it, we are ſure of it: in reaſon, that we eat is the ſame with us: in Religion it is ſo too, and eat it we do, we all are partakers of one Bread.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:112137:25"/>
            <p>That this union is we are ſure of, the Scripture every where beareth witneſſe of it, we could not be branches, he the Vine; not members, he the head; not pretious ſtones built upon him, he the foundation, the cheif corner ſtone; we need not eat his fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſh, nor drink his bloud, <hi>the Cup which we bleſſe,</hi> need not be the <hi>Communion of his Bloud, the Bread which we break the Communion of his Body,</hi> no Communion at all indeed, but for this union: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> might well be ſpared, but for this, <hi>ut uniamur:</hi> it is the ſigne of it, the ſeal of it, the ground of it, the cauſe of it: <hi>ut corpus in terris capiti in caelis:</hi> to make them one, to make this union between Chriſt and us, <hi>Chriſtus erat faciens utrumque in unum.</hi> Chriſts whole work was to do this, to make us one: our nature one in the Hypoſtaticall union; our perſons one in the ſpirituall: <hi>nec pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>judicat rerum plura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litas huic unitati: for we that are many are one bread, and one body,</hi> one bread partaking all of one bread; one body united all to one head: one ſigne, one thing; we all though never ſo many partake of it: <hi>All the beleevers bad one heart, and one minde, Acts</hi> 4. All of them are joyned into one head.</p>
            <p>That this is, that was the firſt: I have been the longer, becauſe it is a matter of ſo much importance, and not ſo eaſily conceived: all our hope of that union, <hi>Quae glorificat,</hi> which the bleſſed Angels and Saints enjoy, conſiſts in this our ſpirituall union, <hi>quae juſtificat,</hi> which is with Chriſt by faith: <hi>illa praemium, haec meritum eſt,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bernard,</hi> all cur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m rit is to be joyned with Chriſt. There is yet ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther work to be done to make this appear: elſe <hi>non apparentis &amp; non exiſtentis, eadem eſt ratio,</hi> as good not be at all.</p>
            <p>And yet, appear we cannot make it, to the eye of ſence, <hi>Caput in</hi> 
               <note n="2" place="margin">Cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſci.</note> 
               <hi>coelis, corpus in terris eſt:</hi> it is much too weak to be able to ken ſo farre; neither indeed is it neceſſary, that the hand or foot ſhould ſee the heal; if they feel it, if they finde the uſe and benefit of it, that will be appearance enough to them: and that is to be had of him.</p>
            <p>Two wayes it will appear.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. By that which the head is to the body. <note n="2" place="margin">Wayes</note>
               </item>
               <item>2. By that the body is to the head.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> There are foure things required to our head, all four to be known <note n="4" place="margin"> Wayes</note> of him. That it be, <hi>1. Verum. 2. Perfectum. 3. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicum. 4. Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuum.</hi> Chriſt is all theſe unto the body.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Verum</hi> of the ſame nature with the body, not like <hi>Nabuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzars</hi> 
               <note n="1" place="margin">Ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Image, whoſe head was of Gold, the breaſts of Silver, the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:112137:26"/> thighes of Braſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, the feet of Iron, and Clay. And that he might be of the ſame nature, you know he took upon him our nature: and therefore God, ſaith the Apoſtle, hath made him <hi>head of the Church, Epheſ.</hi> 1. and that he is of the ſame nature appears. Firſt, by his ſuffering for us; he had not what to offer, till he had <hi>Corpus aptatum, Heb.</hi> 10. he had not been the Saviour of the body, if he had not had that: <hi>Tolle caruem Chriſti &amp; praeſta quid Deus redemit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Tertullian</hi> to <hi>Marcion.</hi> He redeemed not the Angels, <hi>quia non aſſumpſit,</hi> he took not upon him their nature. Secondly, By his ſuff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g with us, therefore ſaith the Apoſtle, it behoved him to be in all things like his brethren, that he might be a mercifull high Pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt. And again, that by the things which he ſuffered, when he was t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mpted, he might ſuccour them that are tempted: for he is not an high Prieſt which may not be touched with our infirmities: when he cryed out upon the way, <hi>Saul, Saul, why pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſecuteſt thou me?</hi> he was neerly touched: he could not be an head, if he had not this, a ſence of the bodies gri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vances. Secondly, Again, to make him a true head, he muſt be united to the body. An head ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vered from the body, is not the head; as good no head at all: a wrong head ſet on, a right head cut off are much a like: the Joynts, and Ligaments, and Nerves, are all for that end derived from the head, that it may be ſet on. And of what nature they are, you have heard b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fore: <hi>Spiritus ſanctus eſt nexus,</hi> and thence is this union called ſpiritull. Thirdly, Again, <hi>ut ſit verum debet eſſe vivum:</hi> a true head, muſt be endued with the ſame ſoul the reſt of the members are; and ſuch is Chriſt our head: the Spirit is the life of both, in the lead that is fully, we have all received from his fuln<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſe: that member which hath not his Spirit is not of his body, his children are led by his ſpirit: <hi>We may know by this, whether we be in him or no, by the Spirit which he hath given us.</hi> A true head we may know him by this.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is a perfect head: ſuch an one which hath, Firſt, <note n="2" place="margin">Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectum.</note> Reaſon. Secondly, Sence. Thirdly, Motion, Fourthly, Soundneſſe. Fifthly, Beauty in it. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l are in him. Firſt, The faculties of the ſoul, underſtanding, will, prudence, providence, he knoweth all things, ſuſtaineth, quickneth, governeth all things. Secondly, he ſeeleth our miſeries, ſeeth our wants, heareth our prayers, ſmelleth our ſacrifices, taſteth our charities, he ſpeaketh and pleadeth for us, mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th interceſſion for us. Thirdly, he moveth us, all ſpirituall motion in the body comes from him, holy d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſires, good works,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:112137:26"/> pure thoughts; in nature, in religion, life and motion, is a <hi>Capite:</hi> We ſee it in thoſe Creatures which are <hi>inſectilia;</hi> cut them in pieces, that part lives longeſt which cleaves to the head, the other ſoon dyes: ſo it is in others: ſo in our ſpirituall body: whatſoever is from the head is dead preſently. Fourthly, He is a ſound and perfect head; ill humours which do infect the body, flow not from him. All is like <hi>Aarons oyl, which runs down from the head to the skirts of the cloathing:</hi> or like <hi>Hermons Dew which waters the Vallies:</hi> His Influence ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h no malignity in it, but rather healing to the members. Fifthly, he is a fair and beautifull head, admits of no deformity, <hi>The faireſt of ten thouſand, fairer then the children of men.</hi> All theſe ſhew him to be a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect head.</p>
            <p>The third, he is an only head, to have no head, <hi>acephali,</hi> to have <note n="3" place="margin">Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum</note> more heads <hi>policephali,</hi> are both a like monſtrous: privations of one, diviſions into many, ever tend to deſolation: God and nature ever affect one, and but one. God himſelf being <hi>Principalis <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nit as,</hi> loves unity beſt, eſpecially in the beſt. And <hi>de ratione capitis est, unum eſſe:</hi> and therefore, God after all things had been ſcattered both in Heaven and Earth by diviſion, by hearkening unto more heads then one, to the Serpents h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad, in the diſpenſation of the fulneſſe of time, would gather them altogether again into one, the word is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. And that is properly a gathering together unto one head; all gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together is into one, as of ſheep into one flock, of materialls for building into one pile, of many numbers into one ſumme, of many grains into one loaf; but none ſo emphaticall, ſo fit in expreſſion, as of many members unto one head; and that one head is Chriſt. Him God hath given to be head of his body, which is the Church: and he is <hi>caput unicum,</hi> only one head: all the heads of divinity, as great Maps in a little compaſſe, as many plots in a ſmall Module, bring them together, contract them to one, they make but one <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> one head, and that is Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The fourth is, he is an head that never dieth, death hath no domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion <note n="4" place="margin">Perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuam.</note> over him: even in Heaven when his body ſhall be removed thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he will do the part of an head. And while there is life in him, he will preſerve it in his body, the Church cannot dye, while her head lives, nor want while it hath ſenſe and motion, and ſpeech, and underſtanding to provide for it: Summe up all that need be ſaid of an head: all is in him, <hi>Verum, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aum, Perfectum, Perpetuum,</hi> all to be ſaid, to be ſeen of him.</p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:112137:27"/>
            <p>We have made this to appear ſufficiently: the Communionis not ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> full, if all come from the head to the body, and nothing back again, from the body to the head; two things it owes to the head at leaſt. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Obedience. </p>
            <p n="2">2. Maintenance.</p>
            <p>Firſt Obedience to be ruled and governed, and moved by the head: <note n="1" place="margin">Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</note> it hath the eyes to ſee, the brain to counſell, the will to put on, and all to be ſit to govern: if it go without the head, <hi>Mole ruit ſuâ:</hi> ſhall the ſoot or the hand ſay unto the eye, we have no need of thee? the Apoſtle makes this his chief argument for obedience, <hi>Epheſians 5. 22, 23. Let Wives be ſubject to their Husbands, for the Husband is the head of the Wife; as Chriſt is of the Church.</hi> The head whereſoever it be, in the body Naturall, Politicall, Spirituall is to be obeyed.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is Maintenance, if the head be hurt or gone, as good all <note place="margin">Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nance.</note> the members be away; be the body never ſo entire, the members right in their places, if the head hap to be away, as good they all aſunder; Therefore all Creatures ſtrive moſt to defend their head; they had rather receive blows any where elſe then there: The Serpent her ſelf expoſeth her whole body to keep, her head from bruiſing; you may mark how ſhe gardeth it with her whole train, the rather becauſe ſhe knows, that is laid at moſt: her head was to be broken ever ſince the prevarication; ſo it is in others: In the body Politique the enemy gives that charge that the Kings of <hi>Aram</hi> did, not <hi>to fight against great or ſmall, but only against the King, 1 Kings</hi> 22. 31. Therefore <hi>Davids</hi> men had a care of him, <hi>ten thouſand of them</hi> were <hi>not ſo good</hi> as he; the light of <hi>Iſrael</hi> was out if he were gone. So it is in other heads. All fencers play is moſt againſt it; it concerns the body to defend it moſt, <hi>ibi fortiter opponere ubi fortiter oppugnatur.</hi> So do Pagans, Infidels, Hereticks, ſtrike at our head; our chief care if it be right, muſt be to defend it againſt them.</p>
            <p>Theſe are due from the body to it: and then there will be <hi>Communis cum <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nione,</hi> which is beſt on both ſides: of ſpirit and life from the head; Of Duty and Defence from the body; it to guide, this to guard; it to lead, this to be lead; this agreement if it be in all things, will make the union to appear ſufficiently, which is <hi>corporis cum capite,</hi> with Chriſt our head. Let us look back once to the ground of this union which is in the Sacrament: by which we that are many are one, one with Chriſt, becauſe we have all partaken of one bread.</p>
            <p>The Communion was for this union: he comes to the outward
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:112137:27"/> ſignes, that by them he may come neerer unto us; if we eat, we have him in us: <hi>niſi manducaveritis,</hi> Yee ſhall not have him in you: and <hi>manducantibus verè ac realiter unitur corpus Christi ſicut panis,</hi> though the manner differ: This corporally the bread is, that ſpiritually Chriſt is.</p>
            <p>It concerns us much then, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that we may be of the other, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>eſſe participes ut ſimus conſortes:</hi> to be of the Communion that which is Sacramentall, to be of it, to be at it, to eat, to eat often, that we may be of this union with Chriſt here, <hi>quae justificat,</hi> which will bring us to that, <hi>quae glorificat,</hi> our bleſſed union with God here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. Whither he bring us all. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="sermon">
            <head>THE FIFTH SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>1 COR. 10. 17.</bibl>
               <q>We that are many, are one Bread, and one Body.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>WE are ſtill upon this theam: <hi>Bonum est nobis eſſe hic:</hi> therefore what the Apoſtles would, we have done: <hi>Aedificavimus tria Tabernacula.</hi> We have ſtaid a time in two of them, we muſt not dwell there, Tents are not for manſions, we muſt remove to the third: <hi>Communio corporis,</hi> which is myſticall, will now take up our <note place="margin">Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>por<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.</note> employment.</p>
            <p>Yet we pitch this upon the ſame ground, we did the other. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is ſtill <hi>cauſa</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, our ſpirituall Communion which is <hi>capitis,</hi> our myſticall Communion which is <hi>corporis,</hi> ſpring from thence, from the Sacramentall, which is <hi>calicis:</hi> we are one bread and one body: becauſe we are all partakers of one bread.</p>
            <p>One body; there it is; we need not ſeek it by induction from the Text, which is there literally, as we did the other, our Communion with Chriſt, <hi>cum capite:</hi> that was as much intended as truly effected as this, though not ſo fully expreſſed. And that muſt have been firſt:
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:112137:28"/> if not for honour which is ever due to the head, yet for neceſſity, we muſt have premiſed that; there could be no talk of the members growing into one body, if they be not firſt united into one head: and in this ſence Chriſt is <hi>caput Eccleſiae,</hi> becauſe all begin there, as the branches at the root, if they be not held to it by Ligaments and Nerves, the skin, the fleſh, and the veins never grow to them, never feed and nouriſh them: But we have done with that, and now the body in its right place comes next to be thought on.</p>
            <p>One body is but one term of the Communion; <hi>duas oportet eſſe eſſentias ad minus, ut ſit Communio, ſeu unitio:</hi> two at leaſt are required to all relation, the <hi>Relatum</hi> is one, but the <hi>correlata</hi> are many, as many, as we are many; there are many members, but one body: though we retain unity there, for the body can be but one; yet we muſt admit of Multiplicity here, the members muſt be many. <hi>Si omnia eſſent unum membrum, ubi corpus?</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle; and ſo they are in the Text. <hi>We that are many, are one Body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ground of this Relation is neceſſarily to be thought on, to make it up, and it comes into the Text; <hi>one Bread,</hi> that is it: the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentall Communion is the cauſe of the Myſticall: that hath ever been conſidered in all the parts of the Text, and the Apoſtle will not have it left out here; two wayes it comes to be conſidered.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As it is the ſigne of it; bread, of the body, one bread of one body: <hi>ſignum unitatis,</hi> Saint <hi>Austin</hi> calls it; for many grains go to make up that; many members to make up this; Bread and Wine both of them, <hi>ex multis rediguntur in unum;</hi> ſo we that are many are one body: this is Sacramentall; and if we read the Text right, as both the Originall hath it, and all the Ancient, both Tranſlators, and Expoſitors render it, tis thus; for there is one bread, we alſo that are many, are one body, one as that is one, ſay <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> and <hi>Ambroſe, &amp;c.</hi> Yet I doubt not but a good Spirit moved our modern Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors to render it as my Text reads it: <hi>We that are many, are one bread, and one body,</hi> one bread firſt; becauſe we all eat of one bread, and <hi>vi fidei</hi> are in a manner become one with that, as <hi>alimentum &amp; Alitum</hi> are one, and one body by virtue of that, one bread ſpiritually, one body myſtically; yet the other is eaſier, leſſe ſtrained, and therefore we will keep to that.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is not only as a ſigne, but alſo as a cauſe of it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is a cauſall; becauſe that is but one, the bread, as the Paſchall Lamb was but one, to all the houſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> one in a Myſticall, and Spirituall
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:112137:28"/> ſence, though <hi>Numerically</hi> many; and we all partake of this one, all the Church of God, all over the world, partakes of one and the ſame bread: in civill commerce to eat of one bread, at one board, hath ever been a pledge of unity and concord; ſo it is in our myſticall ſociety, we are all of one Corporation, one body <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> becauſe we all partake of one bread. All theſe will come to be conſidered in their places.</p>
            <p>We begin with the Text: The Correlatives, <hi>We that are many.</hi> To the Church at <hi>Corinth</hi> are the words directed, but may be aſſumed by us, by all that are in the Church of God, whereſoever they be; place and time matter not in this matter, <hi>nos illi multi,</hi> ſo <hi>Beza</hi> reads it: we are thoſe many.</p>
            <p>We: the Jews, and Turks cannot read this Text; <hi>illi multi,</hi> tis true, too many they are, but ſuch which come together into one, they are not materialls of this building, not ſheep of this flock, not grains of this bread not members of this body, at the beſt they are but of thoſe other ſheep our Saviour ſpeaks of, <hi>Qui non ſunt hujus Ovilis,</hi> or <hi>nondum ſunt;</hi> in Gods good time they may be brought, but as yet are not.</p>
            <p>Beſides them the Schiſmatiques cannot read it, <hi>illi multi,</hi> many they are, ſo many as that the world wonders at it. The Arians and Donatiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s never overſpread the Eaſt and Weſt part of the Church more in their times, then theſe in ours: Like <hi>Egypts frogs,</hi> the whole Land is full of their croakings: But yet they are many ſtill, there is ſome good in that they come not into one, <hi>Quot homines, tot ſententiae,</hi> their perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall differences among themſelves, ſhew they are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> not animated with one Spirit; they would be fearfull to the whole Church if they could be that, and like the <hi>Cake of Barly</hi> in the ſeventh of <hi>Judges,</hi> they might tumble down into the Hoſts and Armies of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and overturn them, but that they cannot be: their Cake which a flaſh of zeal hath heated, will prove dough, or rather like grains, not ground, they will not be kneaded or knit into one Loaf: if at any time they come together, it is with the ſowre leaven of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, and uncharitableneſſe, or of hereticall and Phariſaicall doctrines, the Leaven of the Law, which was to be caſt out; not with the Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of the Goſpel, the Leaven of Faith and Charity. They ſoon fall of having not the right Leaven, into many pieces, being not united by the cement of the Spirit into one Body: ſowing is all they are fit for, and to that imployment the enemy of the Church puts them, the whole field is every where over-ſown with them: Theſe are many, but
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:112137:29"/> not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> thoſe many the Apoſtle ſpeaks of; for thoſe <hi>being many are one bread, and one body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But beſides all theſe, there are many, of whom this Text may be ſaid, which are Materialls of one building, ſheep of one ſold, branches of one Vine, grains of one bread, members of one body: Which though they be diſperſed on the Mountains, are of one flock, belong to one ſhepherd, and know and underſtand his call, though they be as divided members, here one, and that a little one on this Page, and over leaf another, yet being caſt up make but one ſum, are reckoned to one head; though they ly ſcattered like the dryed bones in <hi>Ezekiels</hi> viſion, yet they ſhall come bone to bone, and the ſinews, and the fleſh, and the skin ſhall come unto them, and their breath that they may live, and ſhall be made up into one body; though they be but as an handfull, in compariſon of others in the world, yet like the glean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of <hi>Ephraim,</hi> they are better then the whole Vintage of <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iezer:</hi> A little flock, a remnant, and other ſuch terms the holy Ghoſt calls them by, when he oppoſeth them againſt the numerous multitudes of others; yet they are many, enough ſtones for the building, enough members for the body; God will not let any part be lacking, and there muſt be many members to one body, and here they are many in the Text.</p>
            <p>And that which is above all, <hi>nos illi multi,</hi> we for our parts, and whoſoever elſe which is of the Sacramentall Communion, which is <hi>Calicis,</hi> and of the ſpirituall which is <hi>Capitis;</hi> it needs not be diſputed in what places we are, while we are parts, whether the ear, or the eye, or the hand, or the foot, whether of the honourable or leſſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, while we be members: the adminiſtrations and functions are divers, but they all ſerve the neceſſities of the body. The whole <hi>Church is the Body of Chriſt;</hi> and <hi>we</hi> for our parts <hi>members of it. 1 Corinth.</hi> 12. 27. We may ſure ſay the Text, <hi>We that are many, are one Body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But then that we may ſay it right (and it concerns us much) we muſt know what it is to be one body, what tyes and bonds belong to this union, how neceſſary it is to be of it, what danger there is in being out of it: And this diſcourſe will take up the ſecond part of my Text, The <hi>Relatum,</hi> in which all the <hi>Correlates</hi> meet into one, <hi>We being many are one Body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are divers wayes for many to come into one. Firſt, Naturall; ſo the ſoul, and the body are made one. Secondly, Conjugall; ſo
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:112137:29"/> man and wiſe. Thirdly, Politicall; ſo all the Inhabitants within one City, or houſe are made one. Fourthly, Morall; ſo friends are made one. Fifthly, Hypoſtaticall; ſo Chriſt and our nature were made one. Sixthly, Sacramentall; ſo the ſigne, and the thing ſigned, are made one. Laſtly, Myſticall; ſo all the faithfull, like ſo many members are made one, <hi>being many, are one Body.</hi> I am not to ſay any thing, of any one of them, but the laſt, our Myſticall making one, <hi>one Body</hi> in Chriſt. And this the Scriptures and Fathers have ſought divers wayes to illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate by other Allegories; one building the Materialls many; one flock, the ſheep many; one tree, the branches many: and many ſuch, yet it is but one. The laſt of theſe, I muſt inſiſt upon, <hi>We being many, are one Body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet there are three ſorts of Bodies, eſpecially conſiderable. Firſt, the Body Naturall. Secondly, the Body Politicall. Thirdly, the Body Myſticall. The two firſt of theſe we cannot be, no man will imagine it, in a literall ſenſe, one Body, or in a civill ſenſe, one Body: the Church of Chriſt cannot be one ſo, which conſiſts of many naturall bodies it ſelf, and is in many remote places, never likely to come into one civill Polity, The Body Myſticall is only to be conſidered.</p>
            <p>And that is but Metaphoricall; ſo called by a ſimilitude, taken from the naturall body, otherwiſe it is not properly a body, which is made up of many bodies. But ſo the holy Ghoſt is ſain to ſpeak im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>properly to condiſcend to our capacity, to ſhew us what the Body of Chriſt is, his Church, by that we know already, what the body of man is, <hi>Viſibilibus rapere ad inviſibilia,</hi> ſaith <hi>Gregory,</hi> That is his way. That way we take and conſider four things, belonging to a body naturall, and under that ſimilitude, obſerveable in the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A ſufficiency of parts.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Union of them into one.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Their Symmetry and Agreement.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Their Offices and Adminiſtrations.</p>
            <p>I begin with the firſt: A ſufficiency of parts. No body can be without them, <hi>trina dimenſio,</hi> belongs to every body at leaſt: but a perfect body, ſuch as the naturall body of man is, or the Myſticall Body of Chriſt is, couſiſts of many parts. All the body is not one member, <hi>Multa membra, unum corpus.</hi> It belongs to the Philoſopher, and when he hath done to the Phyſition, to take an exact ſurvey, of all the parts which do belong to a body, it is enough for us, that there
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:112137:30"/> are parts enough. God in framing of the naturall body, would not ſuffer any redundancy or d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iency, we may not but think the ſame of the Myſticall. <hi>In thy Book,</hi> ſaith <hi>David,</hi> unto him <hi>are all my members written;</hi> he keeps a Book of all the members of his body; the Church as well; by him they are numbred, and to him only known; we may not deny the Body of Chriſt to be perfect, which hath a full enume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of parts.</p>
            <p>But yet the parts are not come together to make it perfect, God hath a day Book, <hi>Liber vitae bujus,</hi> wherein lye ſome ſcattered m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers not yet recollected, they are not yet ſummed up, till God comes to his <hi>verbum abbreviatum;</hi> yet they are to be reokoned in the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compts. In nature the generation of the form is in an inſtant, but the parts ſtay their time of production, and when they are all come, the body is not perfect, till it have the degrees: the ſtate of this life is, but the womb of the body of Chriſt, there is a ſtill repairing of the Saints, and an edification of the Body, till we all meet together unto a perfect man. Here as in the Mount, the Materialls are all cut out, and ſquared for that great building; no noiſe of any inſtrument ſhall be heard hereafter, but ſuch ſtones as will ſerve ſhall be laid upon the pile, the reſt put away with the rubbiſh; God only knows how many, and which they be will ſerve; we take all that are any way prepared to belong to it, whereſoever the Axe of the Goſpel, and the Hammer of the Law have come; till the great builder ſhall have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probated them. There ſhall no ſtone be lacking to this building, no member to this Body, though they lye ſca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>terred, yet there will be a Collection: Bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to his bone; though they be wounded, yet there is a repairing, not one of them ſhall be loſt: the hair and nail, and ſuch excrements may well be let fall, and periſh, but no part ſhall be miſſing: A ſufficiency of parts there will be: Tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is the firſt.</p>
            <p>But yet they make not a body, unleſſe they come together, the dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed bones till they were new ſet, and the Nerves, and fleſh, and skin came upon them could not be ſaid a body: ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l the Union of the parts in one come, there is no Communion; many members there be, but by that; and that is the next, they come to be one body.</p>
            <p>In the naturall body there are Nerves, and ſtrings, and ligaments, and irteries, by which all the parts are firmly united; Such there are in the Myſticall by which the body is knit and coupled together in <hi>every joynt; Epheſ.</hi> 4. 16.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. <hi>Spirit us ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ictus eſt nexus:</hi> he is the prime <hi>principall bond.</hi> The
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:112137:30"/> 
               <hi>Tendon</hi> by which all the parts are knit and coupled; The Body to the head by him, and the members to the body: he is <hi>the ſap,</hi> which runs from the root into all the branches, that a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me dyes, and withers, and ſoon falls off, which hath not him; He is <hi>the Leaven,</hi> by which the whole lump is compacted, and grows into one loaf; nothing keeps ſoul and body together, but he; all would ſoon fall off, like ears of Corn, if not by him bound up into one ſheaf: he is <hi>the cement</hi> of the whole building, there is nothing elſe to hinde too the Materialls, if they b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> laid looſe they cannot laſt long: no Union can be firm with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the ſpirit.</p>
            <p>And to this <hi>quaſi ad Tendonem,</hi> all the Nerves and other joyntures tend, here they meet: they are many, as in the naturall body.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. Relig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on is a main tye, it is a <hi>religando;</hi> like <hi>Gordions</hi> knot, it will not be untyed, it may well be forc't. There is a ſtory, how true I know not, yet of no mean Author, how four ſtrong horſes in an whole houres ſpace, were not able to ſtrain the joynts of one man in his ſeverall quarters; and not then, till the executioner with his ſword hackt them in peeces: it is in nothing ſo true as in this tye of Religion. <hi>Non diſſolvi poſſunt quos vera religio conjunxit;</hi> it only makes true Yoak-followes, which like the two Kine, as Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly compares them, bare the Arke of God to <hi>Bethſhemeſh, 1 Sam.</hi> 6. though their Calves were left behinde them, and kept one path, and went up lowing together. Neither Policy, nor Villany, can make ſo firm brethren as Religion: <hi>Fratrum gratia</hi> is no where kept ſo ſure, as between theſe; <hi>Quos Deus Conjunxit,</hi> is ſaid of marriage knot, Let no man put aſunder, let them not, but if they will do it, and it hath been done, who ſhall let them from it? And it is likelieſt done, where both the parties are not of one Religion, or if they profeſſe one, yet they are not, what they profeſſe, both: but of theſe which by it are made one, <hi>quis ſeparabit?</hi> Like <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Jonathan,</hi> they are lovely and pleaſant in their lives, and in their death not divided: neither indeed can they be divided: ſee but what ſtrings they are tyed together with.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. One Faith: <hi>&amp; quiſquis fidem ſe tenere credit, unitatem teneat,</hi> ſaith S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Cyprian.</hi> He falls from that, which falls out of this: Faith is <hi>imitatis Monimentum &amp; Munimentum.</hi> Therefore the Ancients hold that the Apoſtles Creed, <hi>Summa fidei,</hi> was made for that purpoſe: <hi>ut eſſet unanimitatis indicium:</hi> that all profeſſors might there meet in one; though diſperſed never ſo much in place. The Doctrine of
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:112137:31"/> Chriſtian Religion is but one, one Faith materially. The gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t of Faith, by which we have <hi>Faith in the Faith,</hi> to ſpeak with <hi>Athanaſius</hi> Creed; though it be numerically Diverſe, yet is in all but one, one Faith for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally: one Faith, there is union by that.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. One Hope: Heaven, and our eternall inheritance, we all hope for; <hi>one mark the prize of our high calling,</hi> we all contend to; in the world men take divers wayes, becauſe they pitch upon divers ends: he ſaith unto gold thou art my hope; another to his honour: but they that hope all for one thing, like a ſhip under ſail, where there be many paſſengers, ſteer their courſe unto one and the ſame Port Can they think to meet there, and go every one their own wayes heer? As if we had many heads, as one ſaid of the Chriſtian Armies. <hi>Quid abſurdius quàm nos in terris diſſidere qui fruituri ſumus omnes eadem felicitate in coelis?</hi> By one hope there comes more ſtrength to this Union.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. But the <hi>Bond of perfection is love, Coloſſ.</hi> 3. 14. and that is alſo one: it is called <hi>Chriſts garment;</hi> Faith and Hope never go apparreld in any other, and that was, <hi>non de parte conſutilis, ſed per totum textilis,</hi> ſaith <hi>Cyprian,</hi> without any ſeam, not to be ript, nor rent, but delivered whole: If we have that on, and we being Chriſtians would not be thought without it, it will not be too little for us to put on; <hi>ſufficit &amp; mihi &amp; tihi tuni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſti,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bernard,</hi> it will cover us, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all a multitude of ſins, of offences, of breaches, which muſt elſe make us fall off on all ſides. And indeed the cauſe of all our rents is, the want of having that on; and it is not ſuch charity, which we commonly reckon of ſuch which hath but a thread between it, and emnity, or ſo little difference, as that they might not be diſtinguiſhed aſunder. Chriſts Garment is not like <hi>Jeroboams,</hi> wherein were made twelve rents at once: <hi>Integra veſtis accipitur:</hi> the ſouldier to whoſe lot it fell took it whole: men of that calling ſeldomeſt of any have it, yet then it was had to ſhew, that it may be had by men of any condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of that: and being had whole, it will ſerve to cover the whole body; the ear from hearing, the eyes from ſpying, the lips from ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the hands from practiſing any thing, that may tend to the breach of Union, to differences, and diſcention: now a threefold cord is not eaſily broken: one Faith, one Hope, one Love, make the bond of perfection, make the Union firm.</p>
            <p>But beſides theſe three are other which are as Nerves and Sinews to unite all the parts, The Apoſtle reckons them up in <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:112137:31"/>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4. One Baptiſme, The Font is the wombe of our new birth, <hi>ſumus fratres,</hi> As <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaid to <hi>Lot:</hi> It was ſtrange to <hi>Rebecca</hi> to have ſtriving in her womb, but there was ſome reaſon for that, two nations and two manner of people, were in her bowels: But they are all of one people, whom the womb of the Church bears, if they be right bred. Indeed it is not the Baptiſm of Water which makes them one; many Lepers might have waſhed in <hi>Jordan,</hi> and yet not come out as <hi>Naaman</hi> the <hi>Syrian</hi> did: The Baptiſme of the Spirit doth only that, and thoſe that are ſo born, not of fleſh nor of water only, but of the ſpirit, will keep this union, will be one, as that is one.</p>
            <p n="5">5. One Houſe, where we are all brought up together the Church <hi>Domus Dei,</hi> is but one; I ſpeak not of the materiall houſe, but of the myſticall, one Catholike Church, in which we ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k of the ſame breaſts, we are fed with the ſame milk, are tutored under the ſame Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, partake of the ſame Sacrament: <hi>Habitare fratres in unum,</hi> to be of one minde which be of one houſe: this is no ſmall ſtrengthening of the Union. Theſe all of them and many more, are <hi>Eccleſiaſtica vincula,</hi> and belong to the chief <hi>Tendon,</hi> by which this union is made, the ſpirit.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> There are others not to be paſt ore with ſilence: Humane neceſſity, Civill Commerce, naturall Relations, are all of them Ligaments to bring the parts together to make up this union. Religion and Nature both leane to it: Their main intendment is to effect it. And yet when this is done, and the parts joyned, the body is not perfect, if there be not a Symmetry and agreement between them, if they be not of the ſame nature all: twill be but <hi>Humano capiti cervicem jungere equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam:</hi> if not of a juſt proportion, both will be a like monſtrous. Their nature we have touched already, being in one wombe, we doubt not of that: of the other there may be ſome queſtion made, in the naturall Body, it is the wonder of the Creation, to ſee in what perfect meeter all the parts are made; yet there may be ſome aberrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons there; the ſame ſhould be in the myſticall Body: The Body of Chriſt can be no leſſe perfect, and yet the jarring of the parts, as if they had not that Symmetry we ſpeak of, their falling into pieces, as if they were not in their places, makes us make a queſtion of it. Look a little into the cauſe of it.</p>
            <p>God ſaith the Apoſtle, hath ſo tempered the parts of the body, that there might be no ſchiſme, no diviſion in it. but that the members ſhould have the ſame care one for another: he hath done the like ſor
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:112137:32"/> the Church. Apoſtles, Prophets, Teachers, workers of miracles, gifts of healing, helpers, governors, diverſity of tongues, &amp;c. are all of them members of this body; all of them ſet by him in their right places to their right offices. There are divers cauſes of the ſchiſme that is among them.</p>
            <p>Diſlike of their own places: The foot would be the hand; or elſe not of the body: it aſpires higher yet, to be the eye or the ear, in the ſeat of Magiſtracy, as it did of late among the Anabaptiſts in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many:</hi> and in the ſeat of Miniſtery as in the experience of our times. So it was in that great rent of the Body of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in <hi>Jeroboams</hi> dayes, the meaneſt of the people, Mechanicks among them, were made their Prieſts; and if they may not be that, they will not be of the Body, and indeed, <hi>Gratulandum eſt cum tales de Eccleſia ſeparentur,</hi> ſaith <hi>Cyprian: <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tinam abſcindantur,</hi> was Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> hearty prayer. Such were <hi>Corah</hi> and his company: <hi>Moſes</hi> anſwer might ſerve their turns, <hi>Seemeth it a ſmall thing, that the Lord hath ſeparated you, to take you neer to himſelf?</hi> Is it not enough that you are of the Body? Were all the body an eye, where were the ſmelling? Hath not he placed leſſer lights in the Firmament as well as great ones? All are not there <hi>primae Magnitudinis:</hi> hath not he ordered meaner ſervants in his family, as well as greater ones? All are not there <hi>primae diſtributionis:</hi> There will be degrees of glory in Heaven, as there are of places in earth. Beſides to avoide this dangerous ſchiſme, hath not God ſo tempered the body, that he hath given the more honour to that part which lacked? the <hi>onus</hi> is ours, the <hi>hones</hi> yours: The head cannot ſay, unto the feet, I have no need of you; nor the eye to the hand, I have no need of thee: This ſciſme, whether it be in Church or ſtate, one <hi>Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enius Agrippa</hi> in <hi>Livy</hi> very fitly confuted, by telling to the factious <hi>Romans,</hi> the tale of the falling out of the Belly, and the members: becauſe it ſeemed to devour all, the hands would not work, the feet would not ſtirre, the mouth refuſed to receive any food, till they ſound themſelves to languiſh thorough the emptineſſe of the ſtomack, and by bad experience proved the belly no leſſe profitable to the body, then the other members; and that the ſafety of the whole depended upon the ſociety and concord of the parts. This Emulation hath been the cauſe of the diſſentions, which have ever been in the Church.</p>
            <p>Yet there are ſome others cauſes, The neglect of their own offices, and impertinent ſurview of others, which belongs to the head to
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:112137:32"/> cenſure, and not to the parts: The want of Sympathy with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities of the fellow members, if one ſuffer, not careing to ſuffer with him, not conſidering if a Joynt be looſed or ſtrained, all the parts ought to be painted with it: neither of theſe but are cauſes of this ſciſme, and theſe lead me to the fourth particular: the offices and adminiſtrations of the body.</p>
            <p>A ſufficiency of parts, a uniting of them into one body, a placing them in a true Symmetry and Proportion, are all of them for this, for their adminiſtrations and functions, and for them they have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved diverſities of gifts, and by them are to be exerciſed in ſeverall operations: all three are ſpecified by the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 4, 5, 6. All the Body is not one member but many; all the members have not the ſame gifts but divers; all their gifts are not for the ſame operations, but ſeverall: altogether are moſt wiſely diſpoſed, both in the naturall and myſticall Body, for the furniture thereof, <hi>edifying of it ſelf in love, Epheſ.</hi> 4. 16. We have not leaſure now to take a ſhort view of them in particular.</p>
            <p>All that hath been ſaid tends to this concluſion, we are the Body of Chriſt, and Members in particular: <hi>We that are many, are one Body,</hi> a Body in the parts, in the union of the parts, in the Symmetry and Agreement of the parts, in the offices and Adminiſtrations of the parts; and if we be of his body in earth, we ſhall be ſure to be joyned to our head in Heaven; <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpavimus regnum Dei in Chriſto,</hi> we hold Heaven in <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pite</hi> already. But then if we be all one body, there muſt be no ſciſme between us, no falling off from the parts, no falling out without them. <hi>Ad regnum pervenire non poteſt, qui eam quae regnatura eſt, pacem derelinquit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Cyprian:</hi> Hath God tempered them all, that there be no diviſion, and ſhall we diſtemper them by ſciſme, and diſſention? Will it be enough to hang by one Artery, and have the reſt disjoynted? By faith, and hope, and not by love, which is the bond of perfe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tion? If we be wounded, there is a repairing; if looſed or ſtrained, there is a re-eſtabliſhing; if we be of the Body, we muſt have love to all the members, care of them all, we muſt ſuffer with them, ſuffer for them; we muſt cover the blemiſhes, hide the defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of the parts, upon thoſe parts which we think moſt unhoneſt, we muſt put more honeſty, and give the more honour to that part which lacketh. Nature and religion both, can by no means away with a ſciſme in the body. If there be, you be not of the body; you cannot ſay the Text. <hi>We that are many, are one Body.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:112137:33"/>
            <p>And if we be not of this Communion which is <hi>Corporis,</hi> we cannot be of the other which is <hi>Calicis:</hi> that is <hi>Fundamentum Relationis:</hi> and one bread, of one body, and of it <hi>ſumus participes,</hi> we all partake. That of this <hi>ſimus conſortes,</hi> we may be all members; To eat of that, which is one all over the world; as there was but one Lamb to an houſe, ſo but one bread to the whole Church; is the Symboll and Sacrament of one Union with the Body. <hi>Non ex alio tu, nec ex alio ille, ſed ex eodem omnes nutrimur,</hi> ſaith <hi>Chryſostome;</hi> It is but one myſtically though numerically many. And if but one bread, ſhall we make the <hi>Table of the Lord, the table of devils?</hi> And partake of that, with bitterneſſe and wrath? If but one body, ſhall we take the member of Chriſt, and make it the member of an harlot? of ſciſme and contention? God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty grant that we may be all of one minde, in one houſe, being all members of one body; that being united by one Spirit, in one Religion, in one Faith, in one Hope, we may ſerve one God the Father, and one Lord Jeſus Chriſt our Saviour, in one Love, being entred by one Baptiſme, confirmed and ſtrengthned by one Bread, coupled and knit into one Body; there be no ſciſme, no diviſion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, but that all the members have a care one of another, and endeavour to keep the unity of the Spirit, in the bond of peace, Till we all meet together into a perfect man, and the Meaſure of the Age of the fulneſſe of Chriſt. To whom with the Father, and the holy Ghoſt, be all praiſe, and glory, now, and ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="sermon">
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:112137:33"/>
            <head>THE SIXTH SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>1 JOHN 4. 1.</bibl>
               <q>Dearly beloved, beleeve not every ſpirit, but try the ſpirits, whether they are of God; for many ſalſe Prophets are gone out into this world.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I Muſt begin where the Text ends: the laſt words of it are the reaſon of the firſt: <hi>Quoniam</hi> is a cauſall: <hi>Many falſe Prophets are gone out into this world;</hi> Why what then? Only this, <hi>beleeve not therefore every ſpirit, but try the ſpirits, whether they are of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I could not think of any ſubject more proper to this ſeaſon, or more profitable for our ſelves; the old complaint is now, if ever pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved true, <hi>the dayes are evill.</hi> The world was never more rightly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to a Sea, then now; men upon dry Land, as if they were toſſed in a rough Sea, thorough ſtaggering and giddineſſe of their brains, are driven to their wits end: they look thorough the waves of their unconſtant humours, and prejuducate conceits, which make the ſtraighteſt things, which have been ſo well ſettled with mature con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, and unqueſtioned authority, ſeem to them crooked: they complain that the ſhoars and trees are moved, not perceiving how themſelves are ſilently tranſported, and that they move, and not theſe: they do not look that way which they row; and yet as if they ruſhed not faſt enough to their own deſtruction, they hoiſe up their ſails of fury and madneſſe, to precipitate them forward. They think to make away in the Sea, in which they cannot ſo much as ſpye out any prints of their ſteps, which have gone before them, nor muſt hope to leave any impreſſion to be found by thoſe which ſhall follow after. God only knows what Port they are bound for, I fear me the diſtraction, if not diſtruction both of Church and ſtate: what elſe do ſo many fiery diſcurſions abode, the perverting of Scriptures, pretending of Propheſies, wracking of conſciences, the bold determinations of ignorant Mechanicks, flying into the face of dignities and authority;
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:112137:34"/> wounding thorough the ſides of Eccleſiaſticall Diſcipline, the head of Monarchy, and Government? Do they not all huddle in at one gap, to let in confuſion and ruine? Are they not fruitfull ſeeds, which bring forth ſuch a Monſter, which hath ſo frighted <hi>Germany</hi> theſe hundred yeers, and will eat out the very bowels of the Mother which conceived them? Is it becauſe there is no Prophet in our <hi>Iſrael,</hi> at whoſe lips may be inquired the knowledge of the Law? Or is it not rather becauſe there are too many? Such which will take upon them tp be Prophets, and are not called as was <hi>Aaron: Which Propheſie in my name,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>and I have not ſent them, neither did I command them, neither ſpake I unto them, and yet they ran, Jere.</hi> 14. 14, 15. Is not <hi>Saul</hi> among the Prophets, madneſſe and cruelty? And the devill gotten again into <hi>Samuels</hi> mantle, malice and hypocriſie? Is there not a lying ſpirit got into the mouth of theſe Prophets? As was in <hi>Ababs</hi> dayes, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 22. 22. Do they not propheſie lyes unto us, in the name of the Lord? This, this the true cauſe, the Apoſtle tells in the laſt words of the Text; <hi>For many falſe Prophets are gone out into this world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This being the cauſe what Counſell is to be followed? There are two rocks which we muſt neceſſarily avoide: to beleeve all, to beleeve none: by beleeving all, we ruſh preſently into hereſies and ſciſime; by beleeving none, we fall upon irreligion and Atheiſme: againſt the firſt, the Apoſtle gives us a Caution; <hi>Beleeve not every ſpirit:</hi> Againſt the ſecond, this Counſell; <hi>But try the ſpirits whether they be of God.</hi> This is his to them, to whom he writ; this is mine to you, to whom I ſpeak. <hi>Dearly beloved, Beleeve not every ſpirit, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So the Text you ſee plainly ſupplies us with two parts. Firſt, A premonition. Secondly, A premunition. Firſt, For <hi>praemoniti,</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, <hi>Praemuniti.</hi> Firſt, A warning of us, Secondly, An arming of us. They are but two, but we may ſay of them as our Saviour did of the Diſciples two ſwords, it is enough; we need no more, if we be well accoutred with them, if thorowly inſtructed about them; if we know how to prove them, we ſhall by the grace of God, <hi>quit our ſelves like men;</hi> not to be put to turn to the right hand, or the left, but be able to ſtand faſt in our faith, till we be removed from our ſtation, from faith to fruition; from theſe earthly Tabernacles, unto heavenly Manſions; from waging of warre, and wreſtling in combate againſt ſin and errour, to wearing of Crowns, in immortality and glory. We begin with the firſt part, though the laſt in my Text, the Premonition.</p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:112137:34"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Many falſe Prophets are gone out into this world.</hi> It is that which all the Prophets, all the Apoſtles ever complained of, I need not quote you places of Scripture to prove it. Look but into, <hi>Jere.</hi> 14. 14. and <hi>Chap. 23. Verſ.</hi> 21. Our Saviour himſelf foretells us of them, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24. 24. Saint <hi>Peter, 2 C. 2. v.</hi> 1. is evidence enough, <hi>There were falſe Prophets among the people, even as there ſhall be falſe Teachers among you, Which privily ſhall bring in damnable Hereſies, even denying the Lord that bought them, and bring upon themſelves ſwift damnation.</hi> To be told of them aforehand, is the way to take heed of them; to be warned of them, to be armed againſt them.</p>
            <p>And indeed we had need to be warned, there are five reaſons to be yeelded from the very Text, I need not ſeek further for more.</p>
            <p n="1">1. From their name, They are <hi>Prophets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. From their fame, They are <hi>falſe Prophets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. From their number, There are <hi>many falſe Prophets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. From their time, being now preſent, <hi>are gone out.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. From the place whither they are gone, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. I know not what ſpirit moved our Tranſlators, to render the Article ſo ſignificantly, ſure it was a good one: <hi>Into this world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. They are <hi>Prophets.</hi> Who would fear to be ſeduced by ſuch a name? The very name of a Prophet hath been in all ages venerable. Whither ſhould ſhe go for truth but to a Prophet, for inſtruction not deſtruction? But this hath ever been the Devils policy, to bring in damnable hereſies under Heavenly Titles: he which skils to trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form himſelf into an Angel of Light, knows how to make his Agents ſeem like Saints. It is the old Proverb, in <hi>nomine Domini incipit omne malum.</hi> God himſelf complains of it: <hi>In my name have they propheſied lyes, Jere.</hi> 23. The enemy dares not appear himſelf, nor ſend in his own name: <hi>Sub praetextu Divinitatis delit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſcentes omnia polluitis,</hi> as <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> told <hi>Novatus Centu.</hi> 4. This hath been his way, he hath his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, as well as God, he hath been ever ſtiled Gods ape: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore though they be Prophets which come unto us, yet you are to be warned concerning them. that is the firſt reaſon.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. They are <hi>falſe Prophets;</hi> ſuch are all of his ſending, be their ſhews never ſo glorious: the very Mahometanes would be called <hi>Maſlulinen:</hi> the damnedſt Incendiaries ſtile themſelves Jeſuites: the horridſt Treaſon hath been hatcht in a Diſciple: the lying ſpirit comes in the mouth of a Prophet, ſo do wolves in ſheep skins: gilded pills are ever bittereſt; painted poaſts rotrenneſt.</p>
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:112137:35"/>
            <q>Hic dolus eſt magnus, Lupus eſt qui creditur agnus.</q>
            <p>Such as theſe do ſooneſt ſeduce, for they have Syrens voyces, Croco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diles tears, and moſt dangerous they are, becauſe the leaſt ſuſpected. This is another reaſon, and enough alone, if they be proved falſe, to take heed of them: and ſuch as theſe then, falſe Prophets.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. They are <hi>many; Legion</hi> may be their name, as well as his, who is the Maſter of them, <hi>Mark 5. 9. Ye are many,</hi> ſaith <hi>Eliah, 1 Kings</hi> 18. 25. So they were indeed, 450. to one; ods enough. And a little after 400. to one <hi>Michaiah, 1 King.</hi> 22. 6. Our Saviour himſelf notes out their number, <hi>Matth. 24. 5. Many ſhall ſay, Lord have we not propheſied in thy name?</hi> Falſe Prophets all, not of his ſending, ſuch as he will profeſſe unto, that he <hi>never knew them, Matth.</hi> 7. 22, 23. It was the complaint of the Church ſtill. <hi>Many dogs are come about me, Pſal.</hi> 22. 16. And they are falſe Prophets; look to <hi>Iſai. 56. 10, 11. Greedy dogs which cannot underſtand, which look to their own way, for their own advantage,</hi> for their own purpoſe. By the many hereſies they have ſcattered, you may well gueſſe at their number: <hi>Epiphanius</hi> in his dayes reckons up two hundred. Eccleſiaſticall Hiſtories muſter them up by thouſands. In <hi>Luthers</hi> time in <hi>Germany,</hi> they grew to 100000. Now if a ſmall number were to be deſpiſed, yet ſo many may not; we well ſay of the true ones in compariſon of the falſe, as the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples did of the Loaves, <hi>what are thoſe among ſo many?</hi> All our hope is that which the Lord told <hi>Gideon,</hi> he <hi>ſaveth not by many;</hi> This is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reaſon, why we ſhould take heed of them. <hi>Quia multa ſunt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4. They are already <hi>gone out]</hi> like the <hi>Locuſts out of the dark ſmoak, Revel.</hi> 9. 3. In the Apoſtles time, the <hi>myſtery of iniquity</hi> began to work. <hi>Alages</hi> ſince have been peſtered with them. <hi>Semper aut exortae ſunt novae Haereſes, aut renovatae veteres,</hi> hath been the complaint of the whole Church; Satan never ſleeps, he hath like the <hi>Philiſtimes,</hi> his ſpoiling bands ſtill abroad. God hath no ſooner his Prophets out, but he hath his: <hi>Moſes</hi> preſently met with the <hi>Magitians:</hi> they were then, ſo they are ſtill; no times have ever had ſo juſt cauſe to complain as ours: we may take up Saint <hi>Jeromes</hi> cry, changing but the name; <hi>ingemuit tot us Orbis, &amp; Miratus eſt ſe Arianum factum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet is it worth the noting that the Apoſtle ſaith, they <hi>are gone;</hi> true Prophets are alwayes ſaid to be ſent, they go not till they be commanded; but <hi>theſe run, and yet I ſpake not to them,</hi> ſaith the Lord; of their own heads, they are gone out: this is another reaſon, why you muſt beware, <hi>quia multi exierunt,</hi> many falſe Prophets are gone out.</p>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:112137:35"/>
            <p>Laſtly, they are <hi>gone</hi> out <hi>into this world,</hi> all the Emphaſis lyes in the Article: this preſent world, now as well as then: this place of the world, here as well as there: <hi>nullibi ſatis tutum, nullibi ſatis cautum,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bernard:</hi> this world as much as that hath been troubled with them. <hi>Europe</hi> as well as <hi>Aſia: toto diviſos Orbe Britannos:</hi> we which are a world by our ſelves, have a world of them; like the <hi>Frogs of Egypt,</hi> they crawl in all places of the Land; the Kings houſes, the Ovens, and the kneading troughes are not free from them. Here is cauſe enough why we ſhould take warning; <hi>Quia multi,</hi> for many falſe Prophets are gone out into this world. Beſides theſe all from the Text, we might render ſome reaſon out of the Text: They are <hi>gone out,</hi> for what purpoſe think you?</p>
            <p>Firſt, To ſeduce: <hi>non Doctores ſunt, ſed Seductores,</hi> ſaith <hi>Tertullian,</hi> and that they may better do it, they begin as the Serpent did, with the woman; and they creep into their houſes, as he did, for <hi>Serpentis eſt ſerpere:</hi> the Apoſtle ſpeaks it plain, They <hi>Creep into houſes, and lead captive ſimple women, which are laden with ſins; which</hi> women <hi>are ever learning, and yet never able to come to the knowledge of the Truth. 2 Tim.</hi> 3. 6, 7. And that they do under a ſhew of godlineſſe, <hi>making long prayers, Luke</hi> 20. 44. And then,</p>
            <p>Secondly, When they are got in, wherefore come they there? Our Saviour reſolves you; the Wolf cometh not, but to devour and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy; and for that they come, <hi>to devour widows houſes,</hi> their ſubſtance and eſtates: there can be no good lookt for, from their coming, They are of their Maſters Profeſſion, and his name is <hi>Apollyon,</hi> a deſtroyer, and do but mark, how they do ply his work; they deſtroy even foundations themſelves, Faith, Hope, Love, Obedience; and if foundations be deſtroyed, what ſhall the righteous do? Other Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons we might yeeld, but theſe are enough to make us follow the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles counſell, to <hi>mark thoſe which make diviſions and contentions, which with fair ſpeech, and flattering, deceive the hearts of the ſimple, Rom.</hi> 16. 17, 18. Indeed to warne us of them, it is enough alone, but to remember the Text it ſelf: <hi>Many falſ Prophets are gone out into this world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I paſſe to the ſecond part.</p>
            <p>The Premunition.</p>
            <p>To be warned of them, and not Armed againſt them, is to little purpoſe; we may be armed two wayes, by the Text. Firſt, Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, <hi>non credendo.</hi> Secondly, Affirmitively, <hi>probando.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:112137:36"/>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Non Credendo: Beleeve not every ſpirit.</hi> Spirit and Prophet are here <hi>Synonima,</hi> ſo <hi>Beza</hi> and the beſt expound it, Metonimically it is put for him. Every Prophet pretends, he hath the Spirit: <hi>Mabomet</hi> himſelf, that grand Impoſtor, ſtuck not to affirm that the ſpirit was his teacher; By the name of the ſpirit they gain authority unto their Doctrines, So as you have heard already; The devil ſendsforth his agents under the pretence of divinity: But there is a lying ſpirit, as well as a true one, and here we have a caution, <hi>de non Credendo:</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve not every ſpirit.</p>
            <p>It is not ſafe for any ſoul to be too credulous in matters of ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; to beleeve every report, is in civill affairs, an argument of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Levity, much more in religious: Credulity was the ſin of our firſt parents: <hi>Eve</hi> beleeved the Serpent, <hi>Adam</hi> beleeved her. I know when God ſpeaks, to beleeve him preſently; <hi>ea Credulitas ſemper magni fuit &amp; ingentis animi,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome;</hi> it was <hi>Abrahams</hi> praiſe, and the Virgins <hi>Maries;</hi> But ſince lying ſpirits are gone out in the name of God, credulity muſt needs be dangerous: <hi>The fooliſh will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve every thing,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon, Prov.</hi> 14. 15. And the ſonne of <hi>Syrach, Eccle. 19. 4. He that is haſty to give credit, is light minded.</hi> This <hi>de non credendo</hi> then, cannot but be a good watch word. <hi>Beleeve not every ſpirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the reaſon of it is.</p>
            <p>It is alwayes beſt policy to watch that place, where the enimy ſtrives to enter, <hi>ibi fortiter opponere, ubi fortiter oppugnatur.</hi> Satans chief battery is againſt our Faith; we need not fear him much, if he get not in at that: poyſon hath no hurt in it, if it be not received; nor falſe doctrines, if not beleeved: therefore his Agents work moſt upon credulous natures, they commonly begin with <hi>weak and ſilly women,</hi> which are eaſie to beleeve and creep into them, and then by them, winde themſelves into the opinions and boſomes of weak and eff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>minate men. The Devill never could do any thing, if you would not beleeve him: He requires Faith in his Auditors, as well as God doth in his.</p>
            <p>Belief is the only paſſage of all good or evill to the ſoul; if that be eaſie to God, he enters, and with him all graces: if open to the devill, he enters, and with him all vices. Therefore, <hi>Solomon</hi> bids us <hi>keep our heart with all diligence,</hi> and eſpecially that paſſage, at which Satan ſo much ſeeks to enter, which is beleeving.</p>
            <p>And that we may the better keep our heart, we ſhould keep our ears
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:112137:36"/> too: ſtop thoſe outward paſſages, hearken not to them, <hi>Deut. 13. 3. Thou ſhalt not hearken to the words of the Prophets, or dreamer of dreams, &amp;c.</hi> We let him in too neer, if he get into the ear; that paſſage he ſeeks to get firſt: if he can, have free acceſſe to the ear, he will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the heart too, ere he have done.</p>
            <p>And that we may keep both our heart and ear, we ſhould keep our houſes too, not let them lye open to them; it is not ſafe letting them come ſo neer us, their deſire is to creep in there firſt, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 6. But no deceitfull perſon ſhall dwell in my houſe, <hi>He that telleth lyes ſhall not tarry in my ſight,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Pſalmiſt:</hi> and theſe are <hi>Deceivers, Matth.</hi> 24. 5. and <hi>Lyers, 2 Theſ. 2. 9. 2 Pet.</hi> 2. 1. Beloved let me not be miſtaken, I mean thoſe falſe Prophets which are ſpoken in my Text, which are gone out into the world, which come unto you with damnable do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, novelties, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſmes, which ſow diviſions, contentions, debates among you; which call themſelves Prophets, but are not ſent, and come in the name of the ſpirit, but are not to be received; for it is the Apoſtles caution. <hi>Dearly beloved, beleeve not every ſpirit.</hi> But I mean not to inſiſt longer upon this. The ſecond take up more time, which is affirmative. <hi>Probando.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But prove the ſpirits whether they be of God,] There is good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for this rule: to beleeve all tends to hereſie and ſciſme; for there are <hi>lying ſpirits. 1 King. 22. 22. Evill ſpirits, Judges 9. 23. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nclean ſpirits. Luk. 4. 23. Spirits of errour, 1 Tim.</hi> 4. 1. And therefore you have heard of the Apoſtles caution, <hi>de non credendo. Beleeve not every ſpirit.</hi> But yet to beleeve none tends as much another way, to irreligion, and Atheiſme; for there is a ſpirit, which is of God; nay, there are <hi>the ſeven ſpirits of God, which are ſent abroad into the world;</hi> and theſe are to be beleeved, <hi>Revel.</hi> 5. 6. What is to be done, that we may not be deceived? We are now to hearken to the Apoſtles counſell: <hi>Prove the ſpirits, whether they be of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now proving them is all the way we have to be ſafe from errour; the falſe and lying ſpirit comes in the name of God to us, as well as the righteous and true ſpirit: <hi>dicit Dominus</hi> is the prologue ever to their lye. 1 <hi>Kings 22. 11, 12. In my name do they propheſie lyes,</hi> ſaith the Lord himſelf, <hi>Jere.</hi> 14. We cannot but miſtake, if we take all, if we take none: to take the right, is to be take us to the rule; to prove the ſpirits whether they be of God.</p>
            <p>And now if ever we have need of proving, we live in the laſt and perillous dayes, where many ſpirits of errours are gone abroad, and
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:112137:37"/> many are deceived by them; thoſe that are yet free, or not ſo farre gone, have reaſon to be both more thankfull unto God, and more vigilant over themſelves: the name of the ſpirit is able to deceive the beſt and wiſeſt. If a bad one but come, and as once the good ſpirit did, <hi>Gen. 1. 2. incumhehat aquis;</hi> be but incumbent there, or reſt and ſtay there, God knowes what he may produce; it concerns ſuch eſpecially to take heed to this rule: to <hi>prove the ſpirits, whether they he of God, or no.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And it is but the ſame which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> elſe where bids us, <hi>Prove your ſelves, 2 Cor. 13. 5. Prove what things are well pleaſing unto God, Epheſ. 5. 10. That ye may allow theſe things which are beſt, Phil. 1. 10. Try all things, and keep that which is good, 1 Theſ. 5. 21. Try the ſpirits whether they be of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now we go about the Tryall; there are but two wayes that I know of, but both are Demonſtrative; we may not in this caſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent our ſelves with probabilities or poſſibilities: ſhews, and appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances are no good grounds for our ſouls to take any thing upon truſt; our proof muſt be armour of proof, or elſe we ſhall not be well appointed againſt them.</p>
            <p>The firſt is <hi>à Priori;</hi> the ſecond <hi>à Poſteriori:</hi> from their calling, from their converſation; thoſe two are the grounds we can only go upon.</p>
            <p>Firſt, From their calling, for they muſt have that, or elſe they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be right. <hi>No man takes upon him the honour, unleſſe he be called as was Aaron, Heb. 5. 4.</hi> God himſelf renounceth them from being his, if they come, and be not ſent, if they run and be not commanded, <hi>Jere.</hi> 14. If they be not ſent by him, you may ſoon conclude that they be not of God.</p>
            <p>That you may underſtand this point more fully, being a matter theſe times ſo much ſtand upon. You muſt obſerve that there is a two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold calling by God:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Extraordinary.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Ordinary.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Extraordinary, which was in old times: either <hi>ſpiritus Oris,</hi> as <hi>Abraham, Moſes, Samuel,</hi> ſo the all the Apoſtles: They were called by the voyce of Chriſt; and ſent into the world. Or elſe, <hi>ore ſpiritus,</hi> by ſpeciall inſtinct, whereby they were inwardly furniſhed with all the gifts of the ſpirit, neceſſary to that ſervice, whereto they were deſigned, ſo were many of the Prophets; <hi>Elias</hi> in the deplored eſtate of the Jews.</p>
            <p>Theſe wayes of calling are now ceaſed, and not to be looked for.
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:112137:37"/> The Anabaptiſts, and their brood the Browniſts, which pretend Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations and Dreams are not to be regarded: By the inſtinct of the ſpirit of arrogancy and error do they take upon them to prophecy, and of no other ſpirit at all: though they come unto you in a mighty winde, yet God is not in that winde; you may not take thoſe ſpirits to be of God.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. The other way of calling by God, is his Ordinary calling, and that is twofold:</p>
            <list>
               <item>Internall,</item>
               <item>Externall.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. Internall; and that is when a man findes himſelf furniſhed with giſts fit ſor that calling, ſo ſaith <hi>Muſculus</hi> and <hi>Zanchie:</hi> They are the Talents with which Chriſt hath endued him for his ſervice. The ſearch of this is left to every mans Conſcience which deſires the Miniſtery, he ſhall be reckoned an Intrudor, if he finde not theſe in ſome meaſure in himſelf: and therefore in our Form of Conſecration, the Biſhop asketh every one which cometh to be Ordained, whether he do think himſelf to be inwardly called. I confeſſe outward abilities others may judge of, humane learning, skill in Divinity, ſound Intellectuals, by diſcourſe, by examination, they come to be diſcovered; but inward preparations, they are from the Lord: It is the height of arrogancy for any to take upon them to judge of them in others than themſelves, <hi>for what man knoweth the things of a man, ſave the ſpirit of a man which <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 1 Cor.</hi> 2. 11. God onely is the tryer of the heart and reins. He proudly enters into Gods Judgment Seat, which takes upon him to determine that. If it be internall and ſecret, how cometh it known to thee or me? Let other judge of my abilities for the Function, but the preparations of my heart are known onely to God and my ſelf.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Externall, and that is <hi>Mediante Eccleſiâ:</hi> Chriſt hath left the power unto his Church, he called his Apoſtles, they called others after them; <hi>Titus</hi> had precept from <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>ordain Miniſters in every City, Tit.</hi> 1. 5. So had <hi>Timotby</hi> by Impoſition of hands, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. 2. Chriſt cannot be viſibly preſent, the Heavens muſt contain him till his laſt Coming: but by his Spirit he is preſent with his Church, he calls by it: thoſe whom it balls lawfully, we are to acknowledge to be called by God.</p>
            <p>But whether it calls lawfully or no, that is now called in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion; whether this Calling onely belong to the chief of the Church, which are ſo called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or to all the mul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>itude of beleevers:
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:112137:38"/> Thoſe that queſtion it, do withall queſtion the Doctrine of our Church, and if that, which they dare not deny but was well ſetled by uncontroulable Authority, cannot ſatisfie them, how ſhall I? Yet I ſhall adventure to lay my Axe unto the root of this Tree of pride and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogancy, which doth oppoſe it, if ſo be it prove not as the young Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets did, which was but borrowed.</p>
            <p>They that are for a populary election, pretend two Arguments for the Confirmation, The Scriptures, and the Primitive times. I ſhall ſatisfie both with their own principles.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For the Scriptures, their own rule is this; That nothing bindes to a neceſſity of obſervation, which hath not there an affirmative pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept enjoyning it: Let them ſtand but to this, and be tried by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, whether there be any ſuch or no, and whether they do well in impoſing a neceſſity of things which are beſides the rule: Is there any? let them demonſtrate it, and carry the cauſe; Is there none? let them ſee the invalidity and weakneſſe of their Argument, and relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh it. But</p>
            <p>They object the practice of the Apoſtles in their times; there are many things which muſt go to make that an everlaſting rule, and not temporary: thoſe times and ours are not like, and therefore not the like diſcipline: I will name but one reaſon, an eſſentiall one, the true cauſe of that alteration that hath been in this point: All the beleevers were then of one minde, there was no danger of any ſchiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> any rent to be made in the Church then, of which innumerable have been ſince. But yet that they cannot prove: the multitude of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> were preſent, we will grant that, and not onely with ſilence, as ſome think, but with ſuffrages, as others, without which there was no lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on of hands. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is <hi>ſuffragiis creare,</hi> as <hi>Eraſmus</hi> argues in the Election of <hi>Matthias</hi> to the Apoſtleſhip, and the ſeven to the Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſhip: let it be granted they were there, that they ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e not onely ſtill, but ſaid ſome what, but gave their conſent, yet that was onely to their Ordination, not to their Inſtitution, at the giving them power to preach, not aſſigning them any place: and I report me to any indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Judge, whether that be not ſo done in our Churches Form of Ordination.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For the Primitive times which ſucceeded the Apoſtles, we may moſt admite of their inference from thence, which have been ever moſt enimies to true an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iquity: you I now how Epiſcopacy and Ceremony is oppoſed, which themſelves cannot deny, but be grounded in Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity:
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:112137:38"/> we may ſay moſt truly what Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> ſaith, to ſome of the ſame ſort: <hi>Qui in Evangelio, nihil niſi quod vultis creditis; vobis potiùs quam Evangelio creditis:</hi> ſo <hi>vobis potius quam antiquitati creditis.</hi> I confeſſe ingeniouſly there is ſomething favours their ſaying, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally from the <hi>African</hi> Churches, but proves it not to be of a binding nature at all times and places: <hi>Potest eſſe diverſa conſuetudo in diverſis Eccleſis,</hi> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith <hi>Calvin: I condemn not thoſe Churches that have it not,</hi> ſaith <hi>Zanche:</hi> our Church may truly ſay with the Apoſtle, <hi>we have no ſuch cuſtome.</hi> In things which are indifferent (as all things that are not commanded, or forbidden in Scripture are) no man in his right wits will deny, but the power of the Magiſtrate may determine. The Judgement of ſo many counſells, which have paſſed upon this point; The Laws eſtabliſhed in this ſtate wherin we live, are enough to ſatisfie any ſpirit that is not contentious, which defires not rather to ſteal into the calling under the pretence of Antiquity, then to come in by the door of Legall and eſtabliſhed Authority. Of whom we may well ſay, as Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> doth of <hi>Novatus, Adulter &amp; extraneus Epiſcopus ille eſt qui fieri à deſertoribus per ambitum nititur, Epiſt. 52. Sec. 16.</hi> The ſumme of all is, but the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that thoſe which come into their Eccleſiaſticall charges, by thoſe which are in Authority, do come in lawſully, and their calling is of God.</p>
            <p>I muſt not ſtay upon this point which would take up a book, and is not to be contained in a Sermon. I return to my Text: the other way to know falſe Prophets by.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A <hi>Posteriori,</hi> and this is the ſurer, becauſe beſt ſeen by us: it is the ſame which our Saviour gives his Diſciples; <hi>You ſhall know them by their fruits:</hi> give me leave at once, to preſent you with a bundle of them.</p>
            <p>The fruits of the ſpirit are <hi>Love, joy, peace, long ſuffering, gentleneſſe, goodneſſe, faith, meekneſſe, temperance, Gal.</hi> 5. 22. Theſe you may be ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, they are of God: and ſo are thoſe ſpirits, that do come with theſe: But contrarily, the fruits of the fleſh, are <hi>Adultery, fornication, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanaeeſſe, wantonneſſe, idolatry, witchcraft, hatred, debate, emulations, wrath, contentions, ſeditions, hereſies, &amp;c. Verſ.</hi> 19. 20. Theſe ye may be ſure they are not of God, neither are thoſe ſpirits which come with them: Look in another place that true Character of falſe Prophets, and of ſuch which our times are eſpecially forewarned of 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 1, 2.
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:112137:39"/> 
               <hi>In the laſt dayes ſhall come perillous times, men lovers of themſelves, cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, boaſters, diſobedient to parents, curſed ſpeakers, unthankfull, imholy, without naturall affection, truce breakers, falſe accuſers, intemperate, fierce.</hi> And Verſe 5. <hi>Having a ſhew of godlineſſe, but deny the power of it.</hi> And Verſe 6, 7. <hi>Creeping into houſes, and leading captive ſilly wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi> And if you pleaſe to make up their Character out of, 2 <hi>Peter</hi> 2. 1. Such which <hi>privily bring in damnable herefies,</hi> Verſe 3. <hi>Which tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough coveteouſneſſe, and fained w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rks make merebandize of you.</hi> Verſ. 10. <hi>Which deſpiſe government, and ſtand in their own conceit.</hi> Verſe 12. which <hi>ſpeak evill of thoſe things which they know not,</hi> and make their liberty a cloak for their maliciouſneſſe. None of theſe are of God, neither are thoſe ſpirits which do come with them. By theſe you may be able to diſcern them; and this is a tryall you may truſt unto.</p>
            <p>But as in a diſeaſe there may ſome Symptomes be miſſing, eſpecially before it come to be <hi>Epidomicall,</hi> untill it come to the height of it: ſo it may fall out in the diſcovery of this great ſickneſſe of theſe times, all will not appear; eſpecially where there is ſo much art and cunning uſed in the concealing them. I will pitch upon ſome few, which will not fail you, as ſoon as you perceive them, you may be able certainly to prove them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. If they come not in <hi>Love:</hi> the Spirit of God is a loving Spirit: This is the touch-ſtone of the ſpirit: <hi>By this ſhall all men know that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ou are my Diſciples,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>if you love one another.</hi> It is an experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon which our Apoſtle himſelf concludeth a <hi>Probatum eſt: Hereby know we the ſpirit of truth, and the ſpirit of errour,</hi> Verſe 6. Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> is down right, <hi>Quiſquis ille eſt, qualiſcunque ille eſt, Christianus non eſt, qui in Christi eccleſia non eſt:</hi> And in the next words he tells us, whom he means, even <hi>No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atus</hi> the Sciſmatick, <hi>Qui nec fraternam charitatem, nec Eccleſiaſticam unitatem tenuit. Epiſt 52. ſec.</hi> 16. The unity of the Spirit cannot be kept, but in the bond of Peace and Love: thoſe then which come with malice, and contention, and hatred; which come with wrath, and envy, and debate; which are ſuch as the Apoſtle ſpeaks of, ſome <hi>which can never be appeaſed</hi> (pray mark that) <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 30. are juſtly to be ſuſpected, and you may be ſure that they are not of God; and by this rule you may try not only falſe Prophets, but falſe profeſſors.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If they come in <hi>Meckneſſe</hi> and <hi>Humility:</hi> the Spirit of God is an humble Spirit: and it is our Saviour Leſſon to his Diſciples, <hi>diſcite ame quia mitis ſum. I am neer unto him,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>which is of an</hi>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:112137:39"/> 
               <hi>humble ſpirit.</hi> This is another argument to try them by, a Symptome of the Spirit of God: if they come with pride, and arrogancy, if contemning of their brethren, conceiting of themſelves, above them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: you may know by this, that they are not of God.</p>
            <p>Yet there is a voluntary humility, they may poſſibly creep, till they be got in; but this vizard will drop off in a ſhort time, you ſhall ſoon diſcover them by this, whether they be of God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If they come in <hi>Gentleneſſe. The Spirit of the Lord is a gentle Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. Wiſ.</hi> 1. 5, 6. God himſelf came not in the <hi>fire,</hi> nor in the <hi>Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake,</hi> nor in the <hi>ſtrong winde,</hi> but in a <hi>ſoft and ſtill voyce, 1 King. 19. 12. Gentleneſſe and love are the fruits of the ſpirit, Gal.</hi> 5. 22. They know not of what ſpirit they are which come otherwiſe. The <hi>feet</hi> of the Meſſengers of the Goſpel are to be <hi>ſhod with the preparations of peace: Iſaiah</hi> delivers them their Meſſage, <hi>Comfort yee, comfort ye my people,</hi> will your God ſay.</p>
            <p>This is another rule to try the Spirit, it marcheth not ſuriouſly like <hi>Jebu;</hi> it is not madneſſe, but mildneſſe which comes with it. They proſecute their own cauſe, as he did, and not Gods, which come other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.</p>
            <p>Again fourthly, <hi>Truth,</hi> is the tryall of them; the Spirit of God is a Spirit of truth; by their doctrines you muſt try the Spirits. <hi>He that denies that Christ came in the fleſh, is the ſpirit of Antichriſt,</hi> Verſe 3. There are other Doctrines which proceed from the <hi>lying ſpirits.</hi> Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> notes it for a notable one in <hi>Novatus,</hi> for taking upon him to make a ſeparation of the good from the bad, as if he were the ſearcher of the hearts and reins; a lying Doctrine and contrary to the precept of our Saviour himſelf, who commandeth the tares, and wheat, to be let grow together: And to the Apoſtle who ſaith, that in agreat houſe there are veſſels of wood and earth, as well as of gold, and ſilver. Such is the ſhutting up of the Gate of mercy unto a ſinner, after he hath miſſed their ſet time of his call; The denying of hope of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to ſuch as have gone on long in their wickedneſſe, and have faln from their profeſſions: The cutting off, of moſt part of the viſible Church, from a poſſibility of being ſaved, by Gods ſecret and eternall decree of reprobation: deſperate and damnable, and lying doctrines, contrary to Gods own proteſtations; <hi>As I live ſaith the Lord, &amp;c. At what time ſoever, &amp;c.</hi> And the whole tenour of the Goſpel, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed a denying of Chriſts coming in the fleſh; Theſe and ſuch as theſe are but lying ſpirits, and you may be ſure they are not of God.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:112137:40"/>5. I will but adde one more, <hi>If they hate the light;</hi> The privily bringing in their Doctrines, is an argument of ſalfity, 1 <hi>Pet</hi> 2. 1. Our Saviours main reaſon to confirm the truth of his Doctrines was this, <hi>In private have Iſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ad nothing, John 18. 20. Veritas non quaerit angul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r.</hi> The dangerouſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt treaſons have been nouriſhed, and conceived that wayes: All eſtates have juſtly diſallowed of private and frequent convenings.</p>
            <p>The Diſciples were commanded what they had heard in ſecret, to preach it <hi>upon the houſe top:</hi> Theſe dare not do it, for they dare not come to light, leaſt they be reproved. This is another rule if they come privately, if they ſeek privacy they are not of God. Chriſt himſelf forbids you to look after him in the deſert or Chamber. I muſt not adde any more leſt I treſpaſſe too much on your patience; I will ſhut up all in that exhortation of the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom. 16. 17, 18.. I beſeech you brethren mark them diligently, which cauſe diviſion, and offences, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Doctrine which you have learned, and avoyde them: for they that are ſuch, ſerve not the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, but their own bellies, and with fair ſpeech, and flattering, deceive the hearts of the ſimple:</hi> and I conclude, as I began: <hi>Dearly beloved, beleeve not every ſpirit, but try the ſpirits, &amp;c.</hi> Now to the eternall God, who is able to make you ſtand, be all praiſe, &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
